<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plain and brief explanation upon the church catechisme different from what hitherto hath been extant : wherein the first elements and grounds of religion are reduced to such plain and familiar questions and answers ... : to which is added, a plain and useful tract of confirmation / by Nathaniel Blithe ...</title>
            <author>Blithe, Nathaniel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28383</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3197</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5761</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13085754</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13085754</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97303</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28383)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97303)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 408:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plain and brief explanation upon the church catechisme different from what hitherto hath been extant : wherein the first elements and grounds of religion are reduced to such plain and familiar questions and answers ... : to which is added, a plain and useful tract of confirmation / by Nathaniel Blithe ...</title>
                  <author>Blithe, Nathaniel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, corrected.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[16], 66 [i.e. 139] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edw. Millington ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. [2].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Catechisms.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97303:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Plain and Brief EXPLANATION UPON THE <hi>Church Catechiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Different from what hitherto hath been Extant.</p>
            <p>Wherein the firſt Elements and grounds of Religion are reduced to ſuch plain and familiar Queſtions and Anſwers, as are obvious to the meaneſt Capacity.</p>
            <p>To which is added A plain and uſeful TRACT OF CONFIRMATION.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Edition corrected.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nathaniel Blithe,</hi> M. A. Rector of <hi>Dowesby</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edw: Millington</hi> at the Bible in <hi>Little Brittain,</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:97303:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Samuel Parker.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>May 11. 1672.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <p>The <hi>Reader</hi> is deſired to take notice, that that groſs Error, <hi>Page</hi> 16. <hi>line</hi> 7. with which the Author hath been divers times Charged, was a miſtake of the <hi>Printer,</hi> which is now Corrected in this Second Edition, according to the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Copy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:97303:2"/>
            <head>The preface to the READER.</head>
            <p>WHen I conſider what care the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the inſtruction of her Children in the mattters of Religion, both by Preaching, Catechizing, and reading of the Holy Scriptures (whereby plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful proviſion is made for all capacities,) it is matter of very great wonder, that ſo conſiderable a number of Chriſtians ſhould live and dye in that Ignorance, as our own experience too ſadly informs us. Many amongſt us, who although they attain to the full age of Man, yet they are almoſt as Ignorant, even in the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals of Religion, as if they had all their time converſed amongſt Pagans: Poſsibly they can rehearſe the Creed, the Lords Prayer, and the Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by rote, but they are very ignorant of the true ſenſe and meaning of them: Perhaps alſo they may know at large that <hi>Chriſt</hi> dyed for Sinners, and they h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pe to be ſaved by him, but they underſtand
<pb facs="tcp:97303:3"/>not that vow and promiſe they made when they were received into the number of his members, and hereby are ignorant of thoſe conditions which muſt be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by all thoſe that can receive benefit by his meritorious undertakings: this and much more, which would be too long to inſiſt upon, is the ignorance that divers aged Chriſtians groan under. And I know no one reaſon, whereto this wretched igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance can ſo juſtly be attributed, as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the utter omiſsion of that ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary duty of Catechizing, or to the irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and indiſcreet performance of it. And to the very ſame cauſe I am apt, in a great meaſure, to aſſign that wickedneſs and lewdneſs which is ſo confidently and univerſally practiſed amongſt us. Neither is it ſtrange that many ſhould walk ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly, when they underſtand not thoſe Laws and Precepts that require strictneſs and ſobriety in their Converſations: and if we do but duly conſider how apt young and tender natures are to receive any impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, whether ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uous or vitious, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:97303:3"/>not but imagine it to be a buſineſs of very great moment, by Catechizing to inſtruct the younger ſort betimes in the grounds of Chriſtianity: for when vitious habits are by a continued practiſe rooted in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and grown cuſtomary, it will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as difficult to eradicate them, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move a Mountain; and we ſhall hear di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers perſons when they fall into daily groſs miſcarriages, they will preſently be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of their own natural weakneſs, and blaming their original guilt, whereas the main cauſe of theſe their vices pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from a corrupt and ill Education; they are ſo accuſtomed to the committance of evil, that, according to the expreſsion of the Prophet, it is as hard for them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline their vitious courſes, as for the Blackamore to change his skin, or the Leopard his ſpots; and therefore to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent theſe early corrupt inclinations, <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon adviſeth us to train up a Child in the way wherein he ſhould walk;</hi> to ſeaſon his tender years with the ſound knowledge of Religion, and betimes to ſow
<pb facs="tcp:97303:4"/>the ſeeds of goodneſs and vertue in his heart, before it grows hard and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trable; this is the only way to give him a right underſtanding of his whole Duty, whether relating to God, his neighbour, or himſelf; to inform him what he is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and what he is to do, in reference to his happineſs and well living in another world: And this alſo is the moſt compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious way to implant in him ſuch Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox and ſound knowledge, as may fortifie him againſt all the Juglings and Deluſions of cunning Impoſtors; for when they rightly underſtand their Baptiſmal vow, what they are to belive, and that duty they are to perform both towards God and Man; as alſo the Doctrine of both the Sacraments, which our Church Catechiſm plainly and fully treats of; when they have a thorough knowledge of theſe matters en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted in their minds, it will be impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for them to be impoſed upon by every peeviſh Schiſmatick. As unjuſtly as the Papiſts make ignorance the Mother of Devotion, ſo truly may we call it the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:97303:4"/>of Faction. It was the opinion of the learned King <hi>James,</hi> that the cauſe of the miſcarriage of our people into Popery, and many other deſtructive errours, was their ungroundedneſs in points of Catechiſm: neither can it at all ſeem ſtrange, that thoſe Souls ſhould be carried about with every wind of Doctrine, who are not well ballaſſed with ſolid information in the firſt principles of Religion. And upon an impartial enquiry we ſhall find, that the great promoters of thoſe idle falſe opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons amongſt us, are ignorant in a very great meaſure. I confeſs they may have a form of Godlineſs, and a myſterious form of words, by which to expreſs it, that is stuffed with unintelligible nonſenſe; but they are very far to ſeek in the knowledge of the great intendment and deſign of the Chriſtian Religion; they wholly buſie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in prying into the Myſteries if Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, things which neither are profitable nor poſſible for them to know, and in the mean time let ſlip the plain neceſſary du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Religion; and this renders them
<pb facs="tcp:97303:5"/>unſtable in all, their wayes; embracing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſudden fancy as an inſpiration from Gods Spirit, and delightfully entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every fond opinion which a hot-head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Zealot ſhall broach. And therefore if Gatechizing was duly and rightly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, it would lay a good foundation, and implant the wholſom truths of Religion betimes in our natures; and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our knowledge would encreaſe with our years, and hereby we ſhould be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of examining opinions before we em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them, rejecting whatſoever is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to our Creed, or repugnant to that duty God requires of us. There is alſo ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great advantage we ſhall receive by the due exerciſe of Catechizing; this will prepare us for the better underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Sermons, and the holy Scriptures; when by this means a good foundation is layd, then we have ſome Reaſon to hope that whatſoever is built upon it will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper; when we are hereby eſtabliſhed in the plain neceſſary truths of Chriſtianity, this will give us a good inſight into the more
<pb facs="tcp:97303:5"/>difficult myſterious truths of the Goſpel, which are frequently delivered in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. It was a complaint which the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> made of that Church, that they were dull of hearing the deep things of God in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and the reaſon was, becauſe they had not well learned the firſt principles of the Oracles of God, <hi>Heb. 11.12.</hi> And we read in the Acts of the holy Apoſtles that <hi>Apollos</hi> was firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed or Catechized in the way of the Lord (as the Original renders it) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and this made him Capable of Speaking to others diligently the Words of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Seeing therefore theſe are the fruits and good effects of Catechizing, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not aſsign theſe diſorders amongſt us, <hi>viz.</hi> the ignorance of ſome, the debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries of many, the factiouſneſ of not a few, to any cauſe ſo much as to the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of this weighty duty. But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe ineſtimable benefits that do attend this ſo neceſſary a performance,
<pb facs="tcp:97303:6"/>it is too apparent that a very great neglect is made, which is occaſioned not only by the default of Parents, and Maſters of Familes, but alſo by thoſe that are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with the care of Souls; many of thoſe whom God hath bleſſed with Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are ſtrangely careleſs in their Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, being far more ready to debauch their tender years, than to endeavour (by wholſome inſtructions) to ſeaſon them with the ſound principles of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: an idle ſtory, a vain ſong, or a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton expreſſion they can hear repeated by them with far more delight, than thoſe plain neceſſary truths contained in the Catechiſm; and they will on the Lords day rather enjoyn them to employ that time in following ſuch little worldly occaſions as they are capable of, or ſuffer them to idle it away in play and paſtime, wherein they ſhould be rehearſing their Catechiſm be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Congregation: Nay, I fear there are ſome who do abſolutely forbid, or at leaſt ſeek occaſions to hinder their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Servants from being publickly
<pb facs="tcp:97303:6"/>inſtructed in the Church Catechiſm: I would to God that thoſe who are in this nature guilty, would ſeriouſly conſider with themſelves, that almighty God hath not only commanded us to know his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred will, and to retain it in our memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; but alſo to teach it to our Children, and to inſtruct our families therein, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our ſeveral capacities: And certainly thoſe to whom God hath given that great bleſſing of Children, will be ſtrangely confounded, and full of terrour at the great and univerſal day of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when they ſhall behold the fruits of their own loyns rejected with a <hi>depart from me ye curſed,</hi> occaſioned princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally through their careleſsneſs and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect in their education. But beſides theſe, it is too evidently manifeſt, that thoſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo who ſhould feed the flock of Chriſt are very remiſs in adminiſtring ſuch food to theſe tender Lambs as is moſt ſuitable to their weak appetites; and it is very ſtrange they can be guilty of ſo great an omiſsion, if they would but ſeriouſly
<pb facs="tcp:97303:7"/>ponder with themſelves that charge, and duty that is incumbent upon them; that they are ſtrictly bound, if they intend to be accounted good and faithful ſtewards, to give to every one his portion of meat in due ſeaſon: what they can alleage in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence for this their negligence, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to one of theſe heads; either they affirm that <hi>Catechiſm</hi> is an enemy to Preaching, or elſe they do not well relliſh the <hi>Church Catechiſm.</hi> In anſwer to the firſt of theſe pretences, the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> hath not without abundance of Prudence and Wiſdom enjoyned every miniſter under ſtrict penalties to inſtruct the younger ſort in the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> every Sunday in the afternoon; which if due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed, we might hope to ſee a good reformation in the looſe practiſes of the younger ſort. Neither can it enter into my head, how this can poſsibly be an enemy to preaching, in regard it is the moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full way of preaching; and if this was rightly exerciſed, no method could be more proper &amp; ſeaſonable to increaſe the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:97303:7"/>of moſt capacities, eſpecially in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try congregations, where all ſorts are in no mean degree ignorant of thoſe plain common truths contained in our <hi>Church Catechiſm.</hi> The judicious <hi>Mr. Hooker</hi> terms the publique performance of Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in the open hearing of the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, preaching; in reference whereto he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes preaching to be the open publicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of heavenly myſteries, or the making known the ſumme and ſubſtance of the Goſpel; now which way ſoever this is done, whether by a continued diſcourſe, as in a Sermon, or by queſtion and anſwer, as in Catechizing, it may properly enough be ſtiled Preaching.</p>
            <p>But others there are who poſsibly may be convinced, that Catechizing may be advantagious; yet they neglect it, becauſe they cannot affect the Church Catechiſm, which they are enjoyned to uſe. I muſt confeſs my ſelf uncapable of giving ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to this ſcruple, in regard I am altogether ignorant of the reaſons they give in defence of it; I know but
<pb facs="tcp:97303:8"/>one, which is too frequently given in caſes of this nature, <hi>viz.</hi> they do not like it, becauſe it is the <hi>Church Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme,</hi> that is, becauſe it is enjoyned by Authority; it contains no Doctrine but what is Orthodox; and it includes moſt, if not all the fundamentals of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity.</p>
            <p>Three things are required in compiling a <hi>Catechiſme; 1.</hi> That it be plain; <hi>2.</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodical; <hi>3.</hi> That it contains the grounds of Religion; all which are comprehended in the <hi>Church Catechiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> It is plain, and without much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty to be underſtood; all it contains is levelled to the weaker capacities.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> It is Methodical; it begins with our Baptiſm, which is our initiation into Chriſtianity, into the number and ſociety of the Church; it ſhews us what we are by Gods grace and mercy, which grace is given us at our Baptiſm, when as we are made members of Chriſt, Children of God, and inheritors of the Kingdom of Heaven; wherein alſo is implyed, our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb facs="tcp:97303:8"/>by nature, that we are in a ſtate of miſery; our Souls very much defiled, and the faculties thereof very much impaired and weakned by the guilt of Original ſin; it alſo at large explains our Baptiſmal vow, by ſhewing us what we are to believe, and thoſe commands we are to obſerve in order to the faithful diſcharging of that ſolemn promiſe; and then it manifeſts our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency, of our ſelves to do theſe things without Gods ſpecial grace and aſsiſtance, which we are to beg of him by prayer; and here alſo it gives us a rule and preſident for our prayers, <hi>viz.</hi> the Lords prayer; and afterwards in brief it explains both the Sacraments.</p>
            <p>From all which it appeares in the third place, that it contains the firſt principles &amp; elements of Religion; ſo that I cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend what juſt ground of exception can be made againſt the uſe of this <hi>Catechiſme;</hi> but that every Miniſter ought to uſe it, as not only being wiſely and prudently compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but alſo as being hereto obliged by the higher Powers, to whoſe lawful commands we are to yield an active obedience. But</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97303:9"/>
            <p>But theſe are not the only guilty per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>; for beſides theſe there are others to whoſe truſt are committed ſome part of Chriſts flock, who although they do not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>holly omit this duty of <hi>Catechizing,</hi> yet they perform it ſo ſlightly and remiſly, that it is almoſt as good left undone: poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly they will Catechiſe the ſix Sundays in Lent, that is, they will hear the younger ſort by rote repeat over thoſe arſwers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the <hi>Catechiſm;</hi> and when they are able to rehearſe them readily, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them ſufficiently inſtructed in the Catechiſtical points, although they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand very little of the true ſenſe and meaning of what is contained therein; and the truth of this is plain from hence, if you do but propound to them one que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion out of order, is it is not placed in the <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> or vary but a very little in the words of the queſtion from what it is in the Book, they are not able to give an account of it. I wiſh theſe perſons would heartily conſider that Canonical obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence they promiſed when entruſted with <gap reason="missing" extent="2+ pages">
                  <desc>〈2… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97303:9"/>
            <head>A PLAIN and BRIEF EXPLANATION OF THE <hi>CHVRCH CATECHISM.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>VVHat is your name?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. <hi>N.</hi>
               </hi> or <hi>M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why begin you your Catechiſm with this Queſtion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe this name was given me when I was made a Chriſtian; ſo that whenſoever I call to mind this my name, I may remember that I am a Chriſtian, and what thoſe duties are that this my Holy Profeſſion binds me to obſerve and do.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Who gave you this name?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. <hi>My Godfathers and Godmothers in my Baptiſm, wherein I was made a member of Chriſt, the child of God, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97303:10"/>an inheritour of the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>When was this name given you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> At my Baptiſm; and therefore it is call'd my Chriſtian name; becauſe it was given me when I was made a Chriſtian, a member of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Was you then made a Chriſtian?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yes: this favour was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon me at my firſt birth, but at my ſecond; when at my Baptiſm I was waſhed in the Laver of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, then I was made a Chriſtian, admitted into the number of Chriſts viſible members.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In what condition was you then in before your Baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> I was in a weak and infirm ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, the powers and faculties of my ſoul being, in no mean degree, impair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and corrupted.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How came you into this miſerable eſtate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By the fall of the firſt man <hi>Adam:</hi> God made a Covenant with <hi>Adam,</hi> and in him with all mankind; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97303:10"/>God on his part promiſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer on mankind divers mercies; and <hi>Adam</hi> on his part promiſed an exact, unſinning, unerring obedience: but <hi>Adam</hi> by eating the forbidden Fruit, contrary to the expreſs command of his Maker, became diſobedient, and ſo broke the bond of the Covenant, and hereby brought both himſelf and the whole Race of mankind into this wretched miſerable eſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>By what means was you raiſed out of this wretched eſtate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By the meritorious ſufferings of Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> who by taking upon him our nature, and therein performing exact unerring obedience, according to the conditions of the firſt Covenant, and taſting death upon the Croſs for every man, hath hereby ſatisfied for the ſins of <hi>Adam,</hi> and for the ſins of all mankind; and by this means delivered me, with the reſt of mankind, out of this deſperate condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97303:11"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How come you to have a right to thoſe benefits purchaſed by</hi> Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By Baptiſm, which is the Seal of the ſecond Covenant; at the ſetting on of which Seal theſe three Priviledges are beſtowed; to become a member of Chriſt, a child of God, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritor of the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Are all them that are Baptized members of</hi> Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> All that are Baptized in the name of Chriſt, and profeſs the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, may be term'd mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his viſible Body; but thoſe only who, both by profeſſion and practice, are ſincere Chriſtians, belong to his myſtical Body, that is, are uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, live in him, and are infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by his Spirit; theſe are indeed Gods real Children by Adoption and Grace, and ſhall in the end be made inheritors of the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What did your Godfathers and Godmothers promiſe for you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>They did promiſe and vow three
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97303:11"/>things in my name, firſt, that I ſhould renounce the Devil and all his works, the pomps and vanities of this wicked world, and all the ſinful luſts of the fleſh; ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that I ſhould believe all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith: And thirdly, that I ſhould keep Gods holy will and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and walk in the ſame all the days of my life.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why are you bound, according to the firſt part of your Batiſmal promiſe, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Devil and all his works?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe theſe are enemies to God, and hateful in his ſight; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I renounce all that God hates, it is impoſſible that I ſhould be ſo near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly united to him, as to be his true child and member.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is the Devil?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The Devil is an evil Spirit, who once was an Angel of light, but for his Pride and Rebellion was thrown from Heaven, into the horrid Regions of Darkneſs</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97303:12"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What are the works of the Devil?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The works of the Devil are all manner of ſin and wickedneſs, even whatſoever contradicts the Will and Commands of God, and defiles our own Souls.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why are theſe ſtiled the works of the Devil?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe he was the firſt Author of Sin, Rebellion, and Diſobedience; he in the beginning acted it againſt God, learnt it our firſt Parents, and makes it his whole employment daily to infuſe it into the hearts of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What do you mean by the pomps and vanities of this wicked world?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By theſe I mean all manner of ſecular honours, pleaſures and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, all thoſe periſhing delights, and tranſient vanities which this world may preſent unto us, to withdraw our hearts from intending the due per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of that promiſe we made at our Baptiſm.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97303:12"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What are the ſinful luſts of the fleſh?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The ſinful luſts of the fleſh are all thoſe abominations and impieties which our rebellious fleſh luſteth after, and provoketh us to run into.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>The next thing which you ſay, that your</hi> Sureties <hi>promiſed for you, is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve all the</hi> Articles <hi>of the</hi> Chriſtian Faith; <hi>what is it to believe,</hi> or <hi>what is</hi> Faith, <hi>viz. that</hi> Faith <hi>which on your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half was promiſed at your</hi> Baptiſm?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Faith is ſuch an hearty perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the truth of Gods promiſes, and of every thing elſe that he hath ſpoken, as makes us obedient in all things to his commands.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is the object of this</hi> Faith? or, <hi>what is it that we are bound to believe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> I am to believe that Form of ſound words and wholeſom Doctrine, which Chriſt and his Apoſtles deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the World, and that we have epitomized, and briefly ſumm'd up in that Confeſſion of Faith, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97303:13"/>called the Apoſtles <hi>Creed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why is this Confeſsion of</hi> Faith <hi>called the Apoſtles</hi> Creed?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It is ſo called, either becauſe the Apoſtles were the Authors of it, it being compoſed by them; or elſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is an abridgment of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine delivered by the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How muſt your belief of this</hi> Rule <hi>of</hi> Faith <hi>be qualified?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It muſt be intire and univerſal, I muſt neither add to, not diminiſh from this Confeſſion of Faith; but I am obliged by my Baptiſmal vow to believe all and every Article of this Chriſtian Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>The laſt thing which your</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>promiſed for you, was to keep</hi> Gods Holy will <hi>and</hi> Commandments, <hi>and to walk in the ſame all the days of your life: How</hi> or <hi>by what means come you to know the will of</hi> God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> He hath revealed it in his Holy Word, wherein he hath at large mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted how, and in what manner he will be worſhipped and ſerved.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97303:13"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>For what end and purpoſe hath</hi> God <hi>made known his mind unto us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> That we might make it the Rule of our lives, and walk according to that Rule all the days of our lives.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Doſt thou think that thou art bound to believe and do as they promiſed for thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>Yes verily, and by Gods help ſo I will; and I heartily thank our Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father, that he hath called me to this ſtate of Salvation through</hi>
               </hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>our</hi> Saviour: <hi>And I pray unto</hi> God <hi>to give me his Grace, that I may continue in the ſame unto my lives end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How comes it to paſs that thou art bound to perform that promiſe which others made?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe they only made it in my behalf, when by reaſon of my tender Years I was uncapable of making of it in my own perſon; which promiſe I am bound actually to perform when I come to years of diſcretion.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:97303:14"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Are you then able to perform that promiſe, which was made on your behalf?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> I am not by my own ſtrength, but by the grace of God I am; which he hath faithfully promiſed to give to all thoſe that heartily beg it.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What think you of this Eſtate which by your</hi> Baptiſm <hi>you are placed in?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> I think it is an excellent and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Eſtate; as far excelling my natural condition, as light doth darkneſs; the one being a ſtate of death, and the other a ſtate of life.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How come you to have a right to this excellent condition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By vertue of Chriſts ſufferings, who hath purchaſed this condition for me by his Death and Blood-ſhedding, in which by the help and grace of God, I do reſolve to continue unto my lives end.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Rehearſe the</hi> Articles <hi>of thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>I believe in God, the Father All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97303:14"/>maker of Heaven and Earth; and in</hi>
               </hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>his only Son our</hi> Lord, <hi>who was conceived by the</hi> Holy Ghoſt, <hi>born of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered under</hi> Pontius Pilate; <hi>was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, dead, and buried; he deſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> Hell; <hi>the third day he aroſe again from the dead; he aſcended into</hi> Heaven, <hi>and there be ſitteth on the right hand of God the Father Almighty; from thence he ſhall come to judge the quick and the dead. I believe in the</hi> Holy Ghoſt, <hi>the</hi> Holy Catholick Church, <hi>the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of</hi> Saints, <hi>the forgiveneſs of Sins, the Reſurrection of the Body, and the Life everlaſting.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What doſt thou chiefly learn in theſe</hi> Articles <hi>of thy belief?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>Firſt, I learn to believe in God the Father, who hath made me and all the World. Secondly, in God the Son, who hath redéemed me and all mankind. Thirdly, in God the Holy Ghoſt, who
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97303:15"/>ſanctifieth me, and all the Elect people of God.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which</hi> Article <hi>do you learn to believe in</hi> God <hi>the</hi> Father?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This I learn in the firſt Article, I believe in God the Father Almighty, maker of Heaven and Earth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How many</hi> Gods <hi>are there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> There is but one only, the true everliving and eternal God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How can that be, when you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that you believe in</hi> God <hi>the</hi> Father, God <hi>the</hi> Son, God <hi>the</hi> Holy Ghoſt: <hi>How ſayeſt thou then that there is but one</hi> God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In the God-head indeed there are three Perſons, the Father, the Son and the Holy Ghoſt, but theſe three are but one God; and this great truth St. <hi>John</hi> thus expreſſeth: <hi>There be three that bare record in Heaven, the</hi> Father, <hi>the</hi> VVord (that is <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the Son of God, the VVord incarnate) <hi>and the</hi> Holy Ghoſt, <hi>and theſe three are one.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97303:15"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is</hi> God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> God is a Spirit, Infinite in all his Attributes and Perfections.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How knoweſt thou that there is ſuch a being as</hi> God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Several ways: by his wonderful work of Creation, the Heavens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Glory of God, and the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament ſheweth his handy work; but eſpecially by my own Conſcience, which this Infinite Being hath placed within me, to accuſe me of all thoſe Crimes I commit againſt his Divine Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon what grounds do you call God</hi> Father?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> He is my Father by Creation, giving me at the firſt my Being; he is alſo my Father by Adoption, having through the Gate of Baptiſm received me into the number of his Servants and Members.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How did God at the firſt create you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By his Almighty and Infinite
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97303:16"/>Power; by vertue whereof he can do whatſoever pleaſeth him, both in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and in Earth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>And did he finiſh the Heavens and the Earth, and all the reſt of his</hi> Creation, <hi>by his Power and Word alone?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yes: he ſpake, and it was done; he commanded, and they were brought forth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In what time did God finiſh his</hi> Creation?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In the ſpace of Six days, and reſted the Seventh day.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why did God at the firſt give you a Being?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To advance his Honour, and to perform his ſacred Will.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Of what did God make</hi> Man?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> He made his Body of the duſt of the ground, and breathed into his Noſtrils the breath of Life, and ſo he became a living Soul.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which</hi> Article <hi>do you learn is believe in God the</hi> Son, <hi>who redeemed you and all mankind?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:97303:16"/>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In theſe: And in Jeſus Chriſt his only Son our Lord, who was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> ſuffered under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> was Crucified, dead and buried, he deſcended into <hi>Hell,</hi> the third day he roſe again from the dead, he aſcended into <hi>Heaven,</hi> and ſitteth on the right hand of God the Father Almighty, from thence he ſhall come to judge both the quick and the dead.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is this</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>in whom you believe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> He is perfect God, and perfect Man, equal to the Father as touching his God-head, but inferiour to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as touching his Man-hood.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What Relation ſtands this Perſon in to God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> He is his only Son, begotten of the Father before the world, his firſt born from all Eternity.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why did this Eternal God take upon him our nature, and ſo become Man?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97303:17"/>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> That he might Redeem me and all mankind.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>But how can this be, that God ſhould be made Man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> He became Man, not by turning the God-head into the nature of Man, but by taking Mans nature into the God-head, that ſo one perſon might be both God and Man.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What need was there that ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a Perſon as the</hi> Son <hi>of</hi> God <hi>ſhould thus abaſe himſelf?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe there was no other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that could bring to paſs this great work of mans Redemption.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Could none of the glorious</hi> Angels <hi>or bleſſed</hi> Saints <hi>have come down from Heaven to mannage this charitable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It was not in the power of any Angel or Saint, nay not of all the Saints and Angels, to Redeem loſt Man.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why, what was the reaſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In regard none of them was
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97303:17"/>able to ſuſtain ſo great a burden as the ſins of the whole world: He who was infinite in power, as the Son of God was, was only able to bear up under ſo heavy a load: beſides, man, by reaſon of ſin, was condemned to infinite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and therefore no leſs than an infinite God could reſcue man from thoſe eternal torments.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>If none but the Son of God could effect this work, why did he not bring it to paſs by vertue of that Almighty power which appertained to his Godhead, without taking any other nature?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The Godhead is of that infinite perfection, that it cannot poſſibly be ſubject to any paſſion; he therefore that had no other nature but the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, could not pay ſuch a debt as this, the diſcharge whereof conſiſted in ſuffering and dying.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why did he not then take ſome more excellent nature than that of mans?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe it was fit that God's
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97303:18"/>juſtice ſhould be ſatisfied in the ſame nature that had offended: Man onely had ſinned, and therefore it was but juſt, that the ſame nature which had offended, ſhould ſuffer before it could be reſtored.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Did not the fallen Angels Sin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yes, they ſinned, but for them Chriſt died not, and therefore they are reſerved in everlaſting chains under darkneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How comes it to paſs that they an exempted from receiving benefit by his gracious ſufferings?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In regard they beheld the utmoſt of their own bleſſedneſs, but not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, they fell from that glory and happineſs into a rebellion againſt their Creator, without the leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation or temptation, either from any outward aſſault or inward frailty.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What was it that moved God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſend, and his Son ſo willingly to come from Heaven for the ſake of loſt undone ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It was their infinite love, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:97303:18"/>never failing mercies: God ſo loved the world that he gave his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son to dye for it; and Chriſt Jeſus had ſuch a tender compaſſion for the ſinful off-ſpring of <hi>Adam,</hi> that he came down from his everlaſting ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of glory, to open the eyes of the blind, to call them from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Satan, into his own moſt bleſſed kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Did man contribute nothing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the deſerving ſo great a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> No, far otherwiſe; he was then in an open rebellion againſt the King of Heaven; and inſtead of meriting his favour, in ſtrict juſtice he deſerveb the utmoſt of his fury and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How did Chriſt bring to paſs this great deſigne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By ſuffering the puniſhment that was due unto us for ſin, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering and ſubduing all our ſpiritual enemies.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:97303:19"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How did he undergoe this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By his humiliation: He took upon him our nature, was born of a pure Virgin, ſuffered under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> by being crucified on a Croſs; where his hands and his feet were pierced with Nailes, and his ſide with a Spear; And by this his infinite condeſcention and humiliation, he offered himſelf a Sacrifice for the ſins of the whole world.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How did he conquer all our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual enemies?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By his exaltation; he aroſe again the third day a compleat conquerour over Hell and Death, and all the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the grave, and aſcended into the higheſt Heavens, where he ever liveth to make interceſſion for us.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Do you believe then that Chriſt dyed for the whole world?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yes; I do believe that the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Son of God hath redeemed me and all mankind.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97303:19"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How comes it to paſs then that the greateſt part of mankind ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe they are preverſe and obſtinate, they will not go unto him that they may have life, nor embrace thoſe conditions that he offers in his Holy Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which Articles do you learn to believe in God the Holy Ghoſt, who ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth you and all the elect people of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In this Article, I believe in the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What do you believe that the holy Ghoſt is?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> I believe that he is very God, the Third Perſon in the holy Trinity, proceeding from the Father and the Son.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is the office of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It is to ſanctifie all the elect peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why is he ſtiled the ſanctifyer of all the elect people of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97303:20"/>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In regard he is the Author of all holineſs and purity in them; all our inward gifts and embelliſhments pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from him; he is the Lord and giver of life, namely, of that ſpiritual life which is requiſite to actuate and enform every Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How doth he perform this his Office?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Both outwardly and inwardly.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How doth he perform it outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By revealing the Will of God to the Prophets, Evangeliſts, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who by his aſſiſtance and inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have made it known to the world, wherein is contained all things apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining both to life and Godlineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How doth he perform it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By renewing of us in all the parts and faculties of our ſoules, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king heavenly diſpoſitions in them, whereas before they were enclined to all manner of ſin and wickedneſs,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97303:20"/>As alſo by fearing, directing, and governing of us in our actions and converſations, ſo that we may actually perform thoſe things that are accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the ſight of our heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Is there nothing elſe which the Creed propounds to you as the ſubject of your belief?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It alſo teacheth me to believe ſomething concerning thoſe perſons that with true Faith and obedience worſhip the undivided Trinity?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What doth it teach you to believe concerning theſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It teacheth me firſt to believe that there is a Church Holy and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What do you believe this Holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church to be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By the Holy Catholick Church I mean the whole congregation of Chriſtian people profeſſing one and the ſame Faith, far and wide diſperſed over the face of the whole earth.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:97303:21"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Who is the ſupream head and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of this Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Chriſt Jeſus the eternal Son of God, he is the governour thereof, the Rock whereupon it is built; his holy Spirit is the preſerver and ſanctifier of it, and his bleſſed Apoſtles and Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, together with thoſe Biſhops and Paſtors that ſucceed them, do keep and maintain it in the profeſſion of the true Chriſtian faith and religion.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What number is there of theſe Churches?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> There is but one holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that he, when as in the Scripture we read of ſeveral Churches, as the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>the Church of</hi> Corinth, <hi>the Church of</hi> Epheſus, <hi>with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Theſe ſeveral congregations (every one of which is in ſome ſenſe a Church, and may be ſo called,) are properly but one Church, in regard they are all ſubject to one and the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97303:21"/>ſame Governour, they are all built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame Rock, all profeſs the ſame Faith, all receive the ſame Sacralments, all perform the ſame Devotions; which, although divers congregations, yet may they very aptly be reputed mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame Church.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>But beſides theſe ſeveral Churches, we alſo read of a Church Militant and a Church Triumphant; how ſay you then there is but one Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Theſe are but the different ſtate and conditions of the Holy Catholick Church, and not two Churches: In this world it is the Church Militant, and it is ſo termed becauſe alwayes in a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of War, continually fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil; And in the world to come it ſhall be Triumphant, for then it ſhall take poſſeſſion of that heavenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which the Lord <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> hath purchaſed for it, where it's warfare ſhall be ended, and it ſhall gloriouſly triumph over all its enemies.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:97303:22"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How long ſhall this Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To the end of the world. Chriſt from the beginning had, and the end ſhall have a Church, againſt which all the powers of Hell ſhall not be able to prevail, in regard he hath promiſed to be with them always, even unto the end of the world; and then he ſhall receive the true members of it up into glory, to reign with him in his ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting kingdom to eternal Ages.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why do you call this a Holy Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> For divers reaſons; as firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is called by <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and therefore ſeperated from the reſt of the world by a Holy calling. Secondly, in regard all her offices, adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and powers, are ordained to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce holineſs; the Religion ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth is Holy, the laws by which ſhe is governed are holy and good, the offices ſhe performs are Divine. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe whoſoever is called to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97303:22"/>the Faith in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is hereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to holineſs of life. Fourthly, in regard the end of conſtituting a Church, was for the purchaſing an holy and peculiar people to God, zealous of good works.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why do you call this Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>Catholick</hi> ſignifies univerſal or whole, under which term the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Church is comprehended; it being extended to all places and to all perſons. In former time the <hi>Jews</hi> only were the Church of <hi>God:</hi> but now the partition-wall is broken down, and all Nations, and all Perſons in all Nations have a capacity to be of the Church of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What benefits do thoſe receive who are members of his Holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> There are four mentioned in this confeſſion of Faith; the communion of Saints, the forgiveneſs of Sins, the reſurrection of the Body, and the life Everlaſting.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:97303:23"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Who do you mean by theſe Saints?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By the Saints, I mean ſuch perſons as are called by a holy calling, and are obedient to it, ſuch as are endowed with a holy Faith, and purified there by; ſuch as are ſanctified by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>God,</hi> and by vertue thereof do lead an holy and unblameable life; ſuch perſons are truly and indeed Saints.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is that Communion, or wherein doth it conſiſt, that theſe holy Perſons enjoy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The Saints on Earth enjoy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, either with thoſe who are not of the ſame nature with them, as men, or with thoſe that are of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What perſons are thoſe that are not of the ſame nature, with whom the Saints have Communion, and wherein doth that Communion conſiſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Firſt they have Communion with God the Father, they are of his Family, they are his Servants, his Sons,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97303:23"/>and therefore they may with boldneſs ſue to him for his favours, who is as dear and tender over them as a Father is over the fruits of his own Loins.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that Saints living in the Church of God, have Communion with the Son of God; he is our elder Brother, our Interceſſor and Advocate, all our requeſts are put up to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his Name; who by preſenting of them before the Throne of Grace, makes them available for ſuch things as we beg.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Saints in the Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> have Communion with the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> they become Saints and holy men by partaking of this Divine Spirit of life, and by being ſanctifyed by him; he inhabits in them, enlivens and actuates them to the performance of every good and Religious Duty.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Saints in the Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> have Communion with the bleſſed Angels: theſe are thoſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring Spirits, who are ſent abroad to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97303:24"/>Miniſter for their ſakes who are heirs of Salvation: yea, the holy <hi>Jeſus</hi> hath aſſur'd us that they have a particular ſenſe of our condition, enforming of us that there is joy in the preſence of the Angels of God over one ſinner that repenteth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What Perſons are thoſe that are of the ſame nature with the Saints, with whom they enjoy fellowſhip, and what Communion is it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Theſe are of two ſorts.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>which is the first ſort with whom they Communicate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> With thoſe who partake not of the ſame holineſs with them. There was a <hi>Judas</hi> amongſt the holy Apoſtles, and there ever was and will be to the end of the World, ſome Hypocrites in the Church of God; the Tares muſt muſt grow up with the Wheat, leaſt by plucking up the one, they deſtroy the other.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What Communion have they with theſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:97303:24"/>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> They communicate in the ſame Water, being both externally bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed; they communicate in the ſame Creed, both making the ſame open confeſſion of Faith; both agree in the acknowledgement of the ſame Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion; both communicate in the ſame word; both hear the ſame Doctrine preached; they communicate at the ſame Table; both eat the ſame Bread and drink of the ſame Cup which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath appointed to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>If then the Saint and the Hypocrite communicate in the ſame benefits, how then doth the Saint differ from a Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite; or what priviledges doth the one enjoy more that the other?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Although the Hypocrite doth communicate in the ſame externals with the Saint, yet he doth not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with him in the ſame ſaving Grace, nor in the ſame Faith working by love, nor in the ſame renovation of mind and ſpirit.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:97303:25"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Are there no other matters where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they do not communicate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> They do not communicate with the Hypocrite in the ſame ſins, in the ſame accurſed infidelity, in the ſame barrenneſs under the means of Grace, in the ſame falſe pretence and empty form of Godlineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What are the other ſort of perſons of the ſame nature, with whom they communicate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The Saints of God living in the Church, have communion one with another.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Wherein doth this Communion conſiſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> They all communicate of the ſame Ordinances, all partake of the ſame promiſes, are all endowed with the Graces of the ſame mutual love and affection, keeping the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace, all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted into the ſame Stock, and all receive life from the ſame Root.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is the ſecond benefit that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97303:25"/>to be Members of the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Forgiveneſs of Sins.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is Sin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Sin is the tranſgreſſion of the Law of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is the puniſhment due unto ſin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Eternal death: the wages of ſin is death.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Is not all mankind lyable to this puniſhment, in regard, as the Scripture affirms, all have ſinned, and come ſhort of the Glory of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> All mankind was once in a ſtate of death and dammnation.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How then came this benefit of the forgiveneſs of ſins to be made over to them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The Son of God, by his active o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, fulfilling every title of the Law, and by his paſſive obedience ſuffering the wrath of God due to us for the breach of the Law, hath made full ſatisfaction on our behalf, recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled us to God, by vertue of which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97303:26"/>reconciliation our ſins are forgiven.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>To whom doth this favour belong?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To the Members of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Shall all thoſe that are Members of the Church, partake of this benefit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> All thoſe that by Baptiſm are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the Church, by that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, receive the remiſſion of thoſe ſins which they were guilty of before they were baptized; and hence it is that in the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed we profeſs to believe one Baptiſm for the remiſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of ſins: &amp; alſo after they be thus made Members of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they receive remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their future ſins by repentance</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is the third benefit that b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>longs to the Members of this Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The Reſurrection of the Body.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Can the body then ariſe out of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Grave, when as it is mouldred in crumbs and duſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It ſhall moſt certainly ariſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gain, and he re-united to the So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when together they ſhall render an ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>count of all their actions performed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this life.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:97303:26"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Shall the very ſame bodies ariſe that now we bare about with us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> They ſhall be the ſame for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but not for qualities; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they are now Earthly, Mortal, and Corruptible bodies, they ſhall then be Spiritual, Immortal, and incorruptible.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How can this poſsibly be, that the ſame body which is devoured by Worms ſhould again be raiſed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This is performed by Gods infinite and unlimited power, who ſhall call to the dead, ariſe ye dead and come away to judgement; and the dead ſhall hear his voice, and obey it.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>VVhat neceſsity is there that the ſame body ſhould ariſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The ſame body muſt ariſe, and no other, to magnifie Gods juſtice, that ſo the ſame individual body that was a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partner in ſin, may be puniſhed; that which did partake in righteous actions and ſufferings, may be rewarded.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Shall all bodies in general ariſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The bodies both of the Godly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97303:27"/>and wicked, of the juſt and unjuſt, all that ever lived ſhall ariſe, and live again to eternal Ages.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>When ſhall this general reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> At the laſt and great day of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, when the Lord himſelf ſhall deſcend from <hi>Heaven</hi> with a ſhout; and with the voice of the Arch-angel, and with the Trumpet of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is the fourth benefit that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the Members of this Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The life everlaſting.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>To whom doth this belong?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To all in general; for although the life everlaſting is frequently uſed to ſignifie that reward, which in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life is beſtowed upon the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; yet the wicked ſhall live eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What ſhall then be the difference betwixt the godly and the ungodly in this reſpect?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The godly ſhall live to all eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in unſpeakable joys, and never fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97303:27"/>glories; and the wicked ſhall live eternally, or they ſhall remain alive in Soul &amp; Body, to endure the Torments to be inflicted upon them by the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God, for all the ſins committed by them whilſt they were in the body.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Do you think that it is enough barely to believe all theſe Articles of your Faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> As I am bound to believe them, ſo it is my duty to frame my practice anſwerable to this my belief; ſo that I muſt not only know what theſe words ſignifie, but likewiſe I muſt perform ſuch actions as are agreeable thereto.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Is this all that your Baptiſmal vow and promiſe requires from you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> No, it not only enjoyns me to believe all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, but alſo I am thereby bound to keep Gods holy Will and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to walk in the ſame all the dayes of my life.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>When was theſe Commandments given?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:97303:28"/>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> God ſpeak them to <hi>Moſes</hi> upon <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> who wrote them upon Tables of Stone, &amp; made them known to the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for the regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their manners.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>If theſe Commandments are part of</hi> Moſes <hi>his Law, then certainly they were abrogated by the coming of</hi> Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This Law was before <hi>Moſes</hi> was, although not literally recorded; and it ſhall continue after him to the end of the World: and therefore it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Moral Law, becauſe it is to be a perpetual rule of good manners to mankind.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>To whom did God make it known before</hi> Moſes?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> He did implant it in mans nature by Creation; and for this reaſon St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it the Law of Nature: but when mans light and knowledge was decayed and impaired by the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> God again renewed this Law
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97303:28"/>to his Servant <hi>Moſes;</hi> and likewiſe our bleſſed Lord in his firſt Sermon, that moſt excellent Sermon he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched on the Mount, reinforces this Law, and reſcues it from thoſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt gloſſes the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes</hi> had put upon it.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>How many Commandements doth this moral law contain?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>Ten.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>Which be they?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>The ſame which God ſpake in the twentieth Chapter of</hi>
               </hi> Exodus, <hi>ſaying, I am the Lord thy God which brought thee out of the Land of</hi> Aegypt, <hi>out of the houſe of Bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt have none other gods but me.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven Image, nor the likeneſs of any thing that is in Heaven above, or in the Earth beneath, or in the waters un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Earth, thou ſhalt not how down to them, nor worſhip them; For I the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97303:29"/>Lord thy God am a jealous God, and viſit the iniquities of the Fathers upon the Children, unto the third and fourth generation of them that hate me, and ſhew mercy unto thouſands, unto them that love me and keep my Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vain; for the Lord will not hold him guiltleſs that taketh his name in vain.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>
                  <hi>Kemmember that thou keep holy the</hi> Sabbath-day: <hi>ſix dayes ſhalt thou labour, and do all that thou vaſt to do, but the Seventh day is the Sabboth of the Lord thy God, in it thou ſhalt do no manner of work, thou, and thy ſon, and thy daughter, thy man-ſervant, and thy maid-ſervant, the Cattel and the Stranger that is within thy Gates; for in ſix dayes the Lord made Heaven and Earth, the Sea, and all that in them is; and reſted the Seventh day; wherefore the Lord bleſſed the Seventh day, and hallowed it.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:97303:29"/>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>
                  <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that thy dayes may be long in the Land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt do no Murther.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not Steal.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not bare falſe witneſes againſt thy Neighbour.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours houſe, thou ſhalt not covet thy Neighbours Wife, nor his Servant, nor his Maid, nor his Ox, nor his Aſs, nor any thing that is his.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>What doſt thou chiefly learn by theſe Commandments?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>I learn two things, my duty towards God, and my duty towards my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which of theſe Commandments do you learn you duty towards God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In the four firſt, commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the firſt Table.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:97303:30"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which of them do you learn your duty towards your Neighbour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In the ſix laſt, commonly called the ſecond Table.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is your duty towards God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. <hi>My duty towards God is to believe in him, to fear him, and to love him with all my heart, with all my mind, with all my ſoul, and all my ſtrength, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him, to give him thanks, to put my whole truſt in him, to call upon him, to honour his holy name, and his word, and to ſerve him truly all the dayes of my life.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which of the four firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, do you learn to believe in God, to fear him, and to love him with all your heart, with all your mind, with all your ſoul, and with all your ſtrength?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This part of my duty towards God, I learn in the firſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97303:30"/>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods but me:</hi> in which precept I am bound, firſt, to believe that there is a God; ſecondly, I am to believe that there is but one God; thirdly, I am to believe in the true everliving God, and to have him for my God; and when I have thus choſen him to be my God, it can be no leſs than my duty to ſtand in awe of ſo glorious a Majeſty, and to be fearful of diſpleaſing him: and alſo to love him above all things, and for himſelf alone; and to love him not faintly or languidly, but ſincerely and cordially, with my whole mind, with all my ſoul, and with all my ſtrength.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Is this all that you learn from this Command?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> No, every Command, beſides that duty, it poſitively enjoyns, alſo forbids the contrary vice, as likewiſe that command which forbids a vice, alſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns the contrary vertue; ſo that by this command, I not only learn to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in God, to fear him, and to love
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97303:31"/>him, but alſo I am forbidden infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not to believe the one true God, or thoſe Laws he hath delivered to the world; careleſs preſumption, not fearing to offend him; hatred of him, or of whatſoever he commands.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which of theſe four firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands do you learn to worſhip this true everliving God, to give him thanks, to put your whole truſt in him, and to call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This part of my duty towards God I learn in the ſecond Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Thou ſhalt not worſhip any graven Image; wherein, as I am ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsly forbidden, the making any graven Image, or the worſhipping of them when made, ſo alſo I am implici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely enjoyned to worſhip that ſupream infinite Majeſty of Heaven and Earth uprightly and ſincerely, with all bodily worſhip and external forms of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs; to adore him with all humility and reverence, in all my wants to call upon him, who is a ready help in time
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97303:31"/>of need; and when he hath fulfilled my deſires, to give him hearty thanks for his mercies: in all ſtraits and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, to put my whole truſt in him, who is a ſure rock of defence; in a word, in all reſpects to pay him that homage, reverence, and adoration, as his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and goodneſs requires from me.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Wherefore are you bound to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip no Idol, nor any repreſentation of God, but onely the true God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe he is a jealous God, and will not ſuffer the leaſt contempt that is offered to his honour to paſs by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which of theſe commands doſt thou learn to honour his Holy name?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This part of my duty towards God I learn in the third command; Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vain: wherein I am bound to honour Gods Holy Name, by not abuſing of it in my daily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, not uſing it raſhly, fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or vainly in my common diſcourſe;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97303:32"/>not curſing either my neighbour or any of his poſſeſſions in Gods name, not ſwearing by his name falſly, or at all, unleſs it be in a juſt cauſe, before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lawful Magiſtrate, for the deciding of ſome controverſie: As alſo by this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept I am obliged to honour Gods name, by eſteeming highly of it, and ſpeaking of it with reverence and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety; and at all times, and upon all occaſions, praiſing, magnifying, exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and honouring the moſt holy and reverend name of God, his Attributes, or any thing whereby he hath made himſelf known unto us.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What puniſhment do you incur if you are failing in your duty in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> God will proceed againſt me as againſt a malefactor, or guilty perſon; and although poſſibly in this life I may eſcape without chaſtifinent, yet in another I cannot but expect to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely puniſhed.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:97303:32"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which command do you learn to ſerve. God truly all the dayes of your life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This part of my duty towards God, I learn in the laſt of theſe four commands, <hi>Remember that thou keep holy the Sabbath Day;</hi> wherein I am bound to devote that time to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice of God, which the Church by her authority hath ſet apart for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Are you not then bound to obſerve the Sabboth day, that is, the ſeventh day, on which God reſted from the works of his creation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> I am bound to obſerve one day in ſeven as a Sabboth, that is, a day of reſt; but the primitive Chriſtians, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the Jewiſh Sabboth, which was to be aboliſhed after the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Chriſt, made choice of the firſt day of the week on which he aroſe from the grave, to be obſerved as the Chriſtian Sabboth, and alſo honoured it with the title of the Lords day.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:97303:33"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What are the duties required for the right obſervation of this day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> They are two, Sanctification and Reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How muſt this day be Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In muſt be ſanctified by ſetting it apart to the Worſhip and ſervice of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is that ſervice of God which on this day muſt be performed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It may be reduced to theſe three heads, either that publique ſervice we are obliged to perform in the Church; or that charitable ſervice we are to do towards our neighbour; or that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ſervice we are to perform at our own houſes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Wherein conſiſts that publique ſervice of God we are bound to perform on this day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It conſiſts in meeting together at the houſe of Prayer, the Church, and unanimouſly joyning together in the publick prayers of the Church, in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97303:33"/>the word of God read and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, in Catechiſing, and in receiving the Holy Sacrament of Chriſts moſt precious body and blood; and in all theſe offices behaving our ſelves with all reverence, decency, and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Wherein conſists that ſervice we are on this day bound to performe towards our neighbour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It conſiſts in forgiving offences, reconciling ſuch of them as are at va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance, exhorting and edifying one another in love, giving of alms, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting the ſick.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is that private ſervice we are bound to performe to God on this day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Reading good and profitable books, meditating, inſtructing our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies in the principles of religion, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the performance of our private devotions, which is every dayes duty.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:97303:34"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is that reſt which on this is required?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It is a reſt from our common affairs, and all ſervile works and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, unleſs of charity and neceſſity.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Is this all the reſt required on this day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> No, we muſt not onely reſt our ſelves, but alſo we muſt ſuffer our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, our Cattel, and all that belongs unto us to reſt on this day.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>What is your Duty towards your Neighbour, which you learn in the ſecond Table, or in the ſixth following com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>My Duty towards my Neighbour is to Love him as my ſelf, and to do to all men as I would they ſhould do unto me: to Love, Honour, and Succour my Father and Mother: to honour and obey the King, and all that are put in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity under him: to ſubmit my ſelf to all my Governours, Teachers, ſpiritual Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Maſters: to order my ſelf lowly
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97303:34"/>and reverently to all my betters: to hurt no body by Word or Deed: to be true and juſt in all my Dealings: to bear no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice nor hatred in my Heart; to keep my Hands from picking and ſtealing, and my Tongue from evil ſpeaking, lying, and ſlandering; to keep my Body in tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, ſoverneſs, and chaſtity; not to covet nor deſire other mens goods; but to learn and labour truly to get my own living, and to do my Duty in that ſtate of life into which it ſhall pleaſe God to call me.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Who is your Neighbour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Every man, without exception; unleſs the Church of God, by its pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, hath for ſome notorious offence, cut him off from her communion.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Are we then bound to love our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, thoſe that hate us and perſecute us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Theſe we are alſo to love, and hereto we are ſtrictly bound by our Bleſſed Saviours expreſs command: <hi>But I ſay unto you, love your Enemies,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97303:35"/>bleſs them that curſe you, pray for them that deſpitefully uſe you and perſecute you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which of theſe ſix commands do you learn to love your neighbour as jour ſelf?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This general duty I learn in all of them, wherein is contained that kindneſs, mercy, and compaſſion, which one man ought to entertain towards another; it being the great deſign of this Table to maintain amity &amp; friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip amongſt brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which of theſe commands do you learn to do unto all men as you would they ſhould do unto you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This duty towards my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, I likewiſe learn from them all in general, which teach me to give to all their juſt due and right; not to detract from my neighbour by word nor deed, neither to injure him either in body, goods, or name.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which of theſe commands doſt thou learn to love, honour, and ſuccour
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97303:35"/>thy Father and Mother, to honour and obey the King, and all that are put in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority under him, to ſubmit your ſelf to all your teachers, governours, ſpiritual paſtors and Maſters, to order your ſelf lowly and reverently to all your betters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This part of my duty towards my neighbour, I learn in the firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of this Table, or of the fifth in order; <hi>honour thy Father and thy Mother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How can you learn thus much by this precept, when as it onely enjoyns you to honour your father and mother?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Theſe terms <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Mother</hi> are very comprehenſive; under which are included all that are above us, in what relation ſoever, whether natural, civil, or Eccleſiaſtical.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is that duty which this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand requires from you towards your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural relations, that is, your parents?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It is firſt to love them with ſo cordial an affection, as ſo near a relation requires. Secondly, to honour them
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97303:36"/>as thoſe from whom I received my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who take care and provide for me in all reſpects next under my Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. Thirdly; to ſuccour them, if pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence ſhould ever caſt them into diſtreſs, in every reſpect, according to the beſt of my ability.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is that duty which this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand requires from you towardes your civil relations, that is, the King, who is the Father of his Country, and all that are put in authority under him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It is to give them that honour which is due unto them, ſuch as their eminent places and qualities require; heartily to obey all their juſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; patiently to ſuffer the penalties of their Laws when inflicted; never up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any account whatſoever to rebell againſt them, but quietly to ſubmit my ſelf to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is that duty which this command requires from you towards your Eccleſiaſtical relations, that is, towards
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97303:36"/>your Teachers, ſpiritual Fathers, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It is to obey thoſe good inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they give me, to follow their good examples, patiently ſubmitting to all thoſe cenſures, which for my extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies they inflict upon me, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by my true penitency to be abſolved from them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>So then, I perceive there is a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral duty by this command required of you towardes all your Superiours?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yes, this Law enjoyns me to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my ſelfe lowly and reverently to all my betters, that is, to give unto them that due ſubjection, reverence, honour, and reſpect, that their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral qualities and employments chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge from me.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which of theſe commands doſt thou learn to hurt no body by word nor deed, to be true and juſt in all thy deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to beare no malice nor hatred in thy heart?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This part of my duty towards my-Neigbour,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97303:37"/>I learn in the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of this Table, or in the ſixth of them all; <hi>thou ſhalt do no murther:</hi> wherein I am forbidden to offer any violence to my Neighbour, either by word or deed: not to take away his life, either by open force or private treachery, or any other way; neither to harbour any murtherous, malicious, or envyous thoughts againſt him, nor to utter any reviling, railing, bitter ſpeeches: In general, here is forbidden all cruelty or unmercifulneſs either to men or beaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which of theſe commands: doſt thou learn to keep thy hands from picking and ſtealing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This part of my duty towards my Neighbour, I learn in the fourth command of this ſecond Table, or in the eighth of them all; <hi>thou ſhalt not ſteal:</hi> wherein I am forbidden picking, ſtealing, ſecret purloyning, open robberies, violence, plundering and rapacity, or any other way where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97303:37"/>I endeavour to encroach upon the goods and eſtate of my Neighbours: as alſo I am hereby ſtrictly enjoyned to be content with that portion of worldly goods which God hath given me, to uſe juſtice in all mydealings, to preſerve my Neighbours goods, and to ſuffer every man to enjoy his own propriety quietly and peaceably.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which of theſe commands doſt thou learn to keep thy tongue from evil ſpeaking, lying and ſlandering?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This part of my duty towards my Neighbour, I learn in the fifth command of this ſecond Table, or in the ninth of them all; <hi>thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs againſt thy Neighbour:</hi> in which I am forbidden all lying, ſlandering, backbiting, evil ſpeaking, bearing falſe witneſs, and all other vices of this nature, whereby the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation or good Name of my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or his goods and life may be impaired or wronged. As alſo by this Law I am enjoyned the contrary ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97303:38"/>that is, to ſet ſo ſure a guard o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my tongue, as nothing may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed out of my mouth, that may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure my brother.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which of theſe commands doſt thou learn to keep thy body in tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, ſoberneſs and chaſtity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This I learn in the third com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of this Table, or in the ſeventh of them all; <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery:</hi> wherein I am forbidden all manner of ſenſuality, laſciviouſneſs, wantonneſs, or uncleanneſs; as alſo by this Law I am enjoyned to keep my body chaſt and clean from the ſinful luſts of the fleſh, and to make uſe of all means conducing hereunto; ſuch are ſobriety and temperance: and if by a high and full diet my body ſhould grow wanton and unruly, then to bring it into ſubjection by prayer, watching and faſting.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which command doſt thou learn not to covet nor deſire other mens goods, but to learn and labour truly to get thy
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97303:38"/>own living, and to do thy duty in that ſtate into which it ſhall pleaſe God to call thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Thus much I learn both in the laſt command of this Table, and of them all, wherein I am forbidden all covetous deſires towards my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, the envying his wealth or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, all carking over-ſolicitous di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting thoughts in the purchaſing this worlds goods; as alſo, I am by this Law commanded to be content with mine owne, to labour honeſtly in that employment wherein divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence hath placed me, without har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring one evil thought againſt my brothers welfare.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Are you able to keep theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and hereby to make good that part of your promiſe you made at your Baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In ſome meaſure I am able to obſerve them; otherwiſe God would be unjuſt in exacting that obedience I am uncapable of performing.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:97303:39"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How are you able, whether by your own ſtrength, or muſt you have the aſsiſtance of ſome higher power?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> I am not able by my own innate power to obſerve theſe Laws: but that God who commands me to keep them, hath promiſed to aſſiſt my hearty en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours in the obſervation of them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What means muſt you uſe to procure the aſsiſtance of your heavenly Father?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The only way to gain his aid, is by earneſtly and affectionately begging it by prayer; and hence it is that my Catechiſm warns me at all times to beg Gods ſpecial Grace by prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How are you aſsured that God will help you when you pray unto him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In regard that he hath faithfully promiſed, that all ſuch as ask ſhall have; and his bleſſed Son hath paſſed his word, that whatſoever we ask the Father in his Name it ſhall be given unto us.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How comes it to paſs then, that all
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97303:39"/>the requeſts, even of the faithful, are not granted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Poſſibly they may beg ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours as may not be convenient for them, at leaſt not expedient, to be beſtowed upon them at that preſent.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>By what means may we know how to pray as we ought?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Our bleſſed Lord hath left us a form or preſident for the compoſure of our prayers, and therefore it is that we call it the Lords Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>But what warrant have we to juſtifie our ſo frequent uſing the Lords Prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> We have the Authority of Gods holy word. St. <hi>Matthew</hi> bids us when we pray, to pray after that form; and St. <hi>Luke</hi> enjoyns us to pray the very ſame words; from whence we may gather, that when we do not uſe the very words, yet at leaſt we ought to compoſe our prayers anſwerable to that moſt excellent pattern.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Let me hear if thou canſt ſay the Lords Prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:97303:40"/>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name, thy Kingdome come, thy will be done in Earth, as it is in Heaven; give us this day our daily bread; and forgive us our treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, as we forgive them that treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs againſt us; and lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from evil, for thine is the Kingdome, the Power and the Glory, for ever and ever,</hi>
               </hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>What deſireſt thou of God in this Prayer?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>I deſire my Lord God, our heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father, who is the giver of all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that he will ſend his Grace unto me, and unto all people; that we may worſhip him, ſerve him, and obey him, as we ought to do: and I pray unto God, that he will ſend us all things that be needful both for our Souls and Bodies; and that he will he merciful unto us, and forgive us our Sins; and that it will
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97303:40"/>pleaſe him to ſave and defend us from all dangers, ghoſtly and bodily; and that he will keep us from all ſin and wickedneſs, and from our ghoſtly Enemy, and from everlaſting Death: and this I truſt he will do of his Mercy and Goodneſs, through our Lord</hi>
               </hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>
                  <hi>and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay,</hi>
               </hi> Amen, <hi>
                  <hi>ſo be it.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why do you invoke God after this manner, call him your heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe when I conſider him as my Father, this gives me confidence to approach his ſacred preſence; and alſo gives me aſſurance that he will ſupply my wants according as my ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities require.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>But why do you ſay, our Father &amp; not my Father and alſo put up all the following petitions in generall terms?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In regard I am bound not only to pray unto him for my ſelfe, but alſo for all thoſe who have God for their Father.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:97303:41"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>But why do you call him your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in</hi> Heaven?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> To diſtinguiſh him from my temporal Father, and to acknowdedge my being and well-being ſolely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon this my everliving and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Father.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Is their any thing elſe you learn from this comfortable title?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yes, when I conſider that he is in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and I on <hi>Earth,</hi> that there is ſo great a diſtance and diſparity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us; this teacheth me to uſe all reverence and humility, when in his preſence; to have clean hands and a pure heart, when I appear before ſo great, ſo infinite a Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which petition doſt thou beg of God to ſend his grace unto you and unto all people, that ye may worſhip him and ſerve him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Thus much I beg of him in the two firſt Petitions, <hi>hallowed be thy Name, thy Kingdom come;</hi> wherein I deſire that Satans Kingdom may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97303:41"/>and the kingdom of grace daily increaſed, and therefore I pray unto God to ſend his grace unto me, and to all people, that ſo the Devil may loſe ground; and there may daily be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto the Church ſuch as ſhall be ſaved: that ſo all may both in word and deed ſerve and worſhip the true God, and reverently ſanctifie and hollow his glorious Name.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which petition doſt thou beg that we may obey him as we ought to do?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This <hi>I</hi> ask in the third petition, <hi>Thy will be done in Earth, as it is in Heaven;</hi> wherein I deſire that both my ſelf, and all people, may know what is that good, that acceptable will of God, and then make it the rule of our actions; &amp; that his heavenly will maybe performed by us, as it is by the bleſſed Angels in Heaven, that is, chearfully, without grudging or murmuring; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, without delay or procraſtination; ſincerely, without guile or hypocriſie; conſtantly, without intermiſſion; and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:97303:42"/>univerſally, without picking &amp; chuſing.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which Petition do you pray un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, that he will ſend us all things that be needful both for our Souls and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This I beg in the fourth petition, <hi>Give us this day our daily bread;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I entreat God to take us into his fatherly care and tuition, to provide for our ſubſiſtence, to give us daily, or day by day, our bread, that is all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of food and ſuſtenance that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for us; and withall to fend along with it his heavenly bleſſing, that ſo it may nouriſh our bodies, and make them fit for their ſeveral em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Herein indeed you deſire God to give you neceſſaries for your bodies; but wherein do you deſire him to give you neceſſaries for your ſoules?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The Holy Scripture, beſides this ordinary bread, enformes us of bread that came down from Heaven, that is, Chriſt and his benefits repreſented in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:97303:42"/>the holy Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; and this is that bread wherewith we deſire God to feed out Soules, which moſt certainly will nouriſh them to life eternal.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which Petition do you deſire God to be mercifull unto us, and forgive us our ſins?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This I beg of him in the fifth Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, <hi>Forgive us our Treſpaſſes;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I beſeech God to pardon unto me and all his ſervants, all thoſe crimes, offences, and treſpaſſes, what ever we are guilty of.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>But wherefore is that clauſe adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to this Petition, as we forgive them that treſpaſs againſt us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> For very good reaſon; to teach us how we muſt be qualified before we can be capable of Gods pardon; we muſt be in charity with our brethren, otherwiſe God will not be in charity with us; for if we forgive not men their treſpaſſes, neither will our heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father forgive us our treſpaſſes.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:97303:43"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In which petition do you deſire God to ſave and defend us from all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, ghoſtly and bodily, and that he will keep us from all ſin and wickedneſs, and from our ghoſtly enemy, and from ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacting death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This I beg of him in the ſixth petition, <hi>And lead us not into temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but deliver us from evil?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Doth God then lead his ſervants into temptation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> There are temptations of trial or probation, and God doth lead his ſervants into theſe temptations, either to exerciſe their graces, or to chaſtize them for ſome miſcarriage, or to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent them from ſome groſs fall; but beſides theſe, there are temptations of ſeduction and ruine; which the Devil offers, and God by withdrawing his grace ſuffers us to fall into them; and therefore in this Petition I beg of God, that he will continually defend us with his grace, as with a ſheild, that ſo temptations may make no impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97303:43"/>upon; and that he will deliver us from all thoſe ſpiritual evils and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that our ſoules are lyable unto, howſoever occaſioned, whether by the treachery of Satan, by the enticements of this world, or by the provocation of our own luſts; as alſo from the horrid danger that followes our complyance with theſe, the evill of eternal death.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Wherefore is it that you have ſo great confidence and truſt that God will grant all theſe things that you have here prayed for?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Firſt, becauſe his is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, he is the King of all the earth, a loving tender King, willing to hear and relieve the wants of his ſubjects. Secondly, becauſe his is the power, he is a powerful King, and thereby able to give plentiful and ſuitable returns to the requeſts of his humble ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants. Thirdly, becauſe his is the glory, he is a glorious King; and it is a clear manifeſtation of his glory and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to hear from Heaven a company
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:97303:44"/>of miſerable wretches that deſerve no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of kindneſs at his hand; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> ſo be it; reſting fully ſatisfied that God both hears me, and will anſwer my requeſts, as my neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities require.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>How many Sacraments hath Chriſt ordained in his Chrurch?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>Two onely as generally neceſſary to Salvation; that is to ſay, Baptiſm, and the Supper of the Lord.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>When did Chriſt ordain theſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The firſt of them, namely, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, he hallowed in his own perſon, by paſſing through the Waters of it; and alſo immediately before his aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion he enjoyned his Diſciples to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize all Nations: And the other Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament he celebrated with his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples preſently before his Paſſion; and withal charged his Diſciples, and in them his whole Church, to do it in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of him.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:97303:44"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is meant by Baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It is derived from a Greek word which ſignifies to waſh, dip, dive, or ſprinkle.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why is the other Sacrament called the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe it was inſtituted by the Lord of Glory, at or after ſupper.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How or in what ſenſe are theſe Sacraments generally neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> They are the Inſtruments, or the means whereby the merits of Chriſt are conveyed and made over to us, and by which God hath commanded us to receive them; and therefore thoſe that wilfully refuſe and neglect them when they may be had, do neglect the ordinary means of Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>What do you mean by this. word</hi>
               </hi> Sacrament?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>I mean an outward viſible ſign of an inward ſpiritual grace, given unto us, ordained by Chriſt himſelf as a means
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:97303:45"/>whereby we receive the ſame, and a pledge to aſſure us thereof.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is the end or final cauſe why Chriſt ordained Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> He ordained them as a means whereby great bleſſings and graces are conveyed to us, and as a pledge to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us of his favour and loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is that grace which by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments is conveyed unto us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The whole obedience, merit, death and paſſion of our Saviour, and the benefits that flow from thence.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Is Chriſt alone the ordainer of Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> He onely hath right to inſtitute a Sacrament, in regard he is the ſole Author of thoſe graces, that by Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are made over to true belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>How many parts are there in a Sacrament.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>Two, the outward viſible ſign, and the inward ſpiritual grace.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:97303:45"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why are the one part in theſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, namely, water in Baptiſm, and bread and wine in the Lord Supper, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med outward and viſible ſigns?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> They are termed outward and viſible, in regard they are apparent to our ſenſes, no eye but ſeeth them; and they are called ſigns, becauſe they are reſemblances of ſome higher things, ſignifie or ſpecifie ſome favours that by them are conferred upon mankind.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>Wherefore is the other part of theſe Sacraments ſtiled an inward and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It is termed inward inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe it is not to be diſcerned by the eye of men, but it is repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us by theſe ſigns; and therefore it is called a grace, becauſe the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits that by theſe Sacraments are made over unto us, proceed from the meer grace and mercy of God through Je-Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:97303:46"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>What is the outward viſible form or ſign in Baptiſm?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>Water, wherein the perſon Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized is dipped, or ſprinkled with it, in the name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What Analogy or proportion doth this outward Sign, Water, bear to the thing ſignified?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Very much, Baptiſm is the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing away of ſin; and therefore the outward waſhing in water doth very fitly repreſent the inward waſhing of our Souls, both from the guilt and ſpot of ſin in the blood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Wherefore is Baptiſm adminiſtred in the Name of the Father, of the Son, and of the holy Ghoſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This is done for divers weighty reaſons. Firſt, that the congregation may know that what the Miniſter doth, he doth not of or from himſelf, but by commiſſion and good authority, even by the authority of the whole Trinity. Secondly, This is done for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:97303:46"/>of the Baptized, in regard they may be aſſured, that the whole Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity do ratifie and confirm what is promiſed in Baptiſm, <hi>viz.</hi> remiſſion of Sins, and acceptance into Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This is done to lay a ſtrict obligation on the party Baptized, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and believe in theſe three perſons, and to deliver up himſelf to follow the inſtructions of theſe, and no other, in the myſteries of Religion; to be obedient to their injunctions, and to aſcribe all honour and glory to the whole Trinity.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>What is the inward ſpiritual grace in Baptiſm?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>A death unto ſin, and a new birth unto righteouſneſs; for being by nature born in ſin, and the children of wrath, we are hereby made the children of grace.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What do you mean by a death unto ſin, and a new birth unto righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, which you ſay is the inward
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97303:47"/>grace given you in baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By a death unto ſin, I mean, a get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out of the power, and from under the guilt and puniſhment of ſin: And by a new birth unto righteouſneſs, I mean a denying all our former un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs and worldly luſts, and a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſoberly righteouſly and godly in this preſent evil world.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>But how is baptiſm a means of working this in us, and a pledge to aſſure us thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In regard in Baptiſm there is that meaſure of ſtrength given us by Chriſt as will enable us to get out of that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile dangerous condition, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding before the adminiſtration of this Sacrament we were in a ſtate of ſin, and children of wrath, that is, had ſtrong inclinations and violent propenſions to evil; yet hereby we are made chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of grace, that is, are endowed with a ſufficiency of power and ſtrength to walk as children of light.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:97303:47"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>What is required of perſons to be baptiſed.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>Repentance, whereby they forſake ſin; and faith, whereby they ſtedfaſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the promiſes of God made to them in that Sacrament.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why is Repentance a neceſſary qualification to baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In regard we then change our condition, we are received from an eſtate of wrath into an eſtate of grace and favour; and therefore it is requiſite we ſhould change our minds, after their diſpoſitions &amp; inclinations, as alſo this grace is neceſſary, becauſe it diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth us, and makes us capable of the mercies in Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is Repentance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Repentance is a turning from ſin to God, and it is ſuch a ſincere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance as this that is required before Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>The other qualification is faith; wherein lyeth the neceſſity of this grace to diſpoſe us for Baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:97303:48"/>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It lies in this, becauſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God have not their effect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, unleſs they are accepted by us, and it is Faith only that can apply them; and therefore it is neceſſary that thoſe who partake of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould by Faith believe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God made to them in that Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>Why then are Infants Baptized, when by reaſon of their tender years they cannot perform theſe conditions, that is, they cannot Repent and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>Becauſe they promiſe the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of both theſe by their ſureties; which promiſe, when they come at age themſelves are bound to perform.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>But what power hath the Church of God to adminiſter this Sacrament to Infants, meerly upon the engagement of others for the performance of theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Herein the Church follows the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:97303:48"/>example of our Saviour Chriſt; who commanded young children to be brought unto him, when by reaſon of their tender years they were uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of coming themſelves; and although they could not in that capacity, by any act of their own, diſpoſe themſeves for his favors, yet he took them up in his arms, as Miniſters do Infants; laid his hands upon them, as the Miniſter doth water; and bleſſed them, as his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters pray over them, and for them; and our Saviour affirms that of ſuch is the kingdome of Heaven, that is, thoſe who do not receive it as little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that is, with innocence, without any let or hinderance, cannot enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it: and in conformity to this great exemplar, the Church admits Infants (in regard they are part of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, that is, to them it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs) into the Covenant of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, by ſetting on the ſeal of it, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, when they are not in a capacity themſelves actually to repent and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:97303:49"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>But ſuppoſe infants do not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form this promiſe made on their behalf when they come at age?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Then they forfeit that grace gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in Baptiſm: For Baptiſm is a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, wherein God makes over to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind divers favours; and man on his part promiſes an entire forſaking of ſin, a ſtedfaſt believing of Gods word, and a hearty obedience to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; now man by breaking his part of the Covenant, forfeits his right to thoſe favours by it held forth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>Why was the Sacrament of the Lords Supper ordained?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>For the continual remembrance of the Sacrifice of the death of Chriſt, and of the benefits we receive there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why do you call the death of Chriſt a Sacrifice?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In regard he freely offered up himſelf upon the Croſs, as a Sacrifice, to make explation and ſatisfaction for the ſins of the World.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:97303:49"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How is this Sacrament a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of this Sacrifice?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In regard in this Sacrament we have as it were Chriſt crucified before our eyes, repreſented lively before us on the Croſs: when the bread is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, it calls to mind how his ſacred body was broken with the Crown of Thorns, the ſcourges, the nails, the ſpear; and when the wine is poured out, it remembers us how his precious blood iſſued forth out of his hands, feet, head and ſide.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What other end was thereof Chriſts inſtituting this holy Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> For the remembrance of thoſe benefits we receive by the ſacrifice of his death and paſſion; that is, that we ſhould continually, that is, frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remember and commemorate with joy and thankſgiving before God and man, thoſe benefits purchaſed by his death.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>What is the outward part or ſign of the Lords Supper?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:97303:50"/>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>Bread and Wine, which the Lord hath commanded to be received.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Why are theſe two Elements ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than any other uſed in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe theſe do very fitly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the inward ſpiritual grace, which is the body and blood of Chriſt. As Bread and Wine is the cheif nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of our Bodies, the great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatives of life and health, ſo the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Blood of Chriſt is the onely food of our Soules, which muſt houriſh them to life eternal.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Where hath the Lord commanded theſe elements to be received?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> At his firſt inſtitution of it, he gave this command to his holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and in them to his whole Church; <hi>when he had broke the bread, he gave it unto them, and ſaid, take, eat, this is my body; and when he had bleſſed the cup, he gave it them, ſaying, drink ye all of this.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:97303:50"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>What is the inward part, or thing ſignified in this Sacrament.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>The Body and Blood of Chriſt, which are verily and indeed taken and received by the Faithful in the Lords Supper.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How can it poſſibly be that the very body and blood of Chriſt can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the Lord Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In this Sacrament there is a true and real participation of Chriſt, for as verily as every worthy communicant eats the Bread, and drinks the Wine, ſo verily God in heaven beſtows on him, and communicates unto him the body and blood of his Saviour; and alſo makes over unto him all the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and advantages that proceed from the ſufferings of his body, and the effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his Blood.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>By whom is it that the body and blood of Chriſt are verily and indeed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in this holy Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It is onely by the faithful; that
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:97303:51"/>is, ſuch as worthily prepare themſelves before they adventure to preſent themſelves, that behave themſelves de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly and reverently in the time of the adminiſtration of it, and alſo after the receiving of it, walk as becometh ſuch who are united to Chriſt by ſo near a tye.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Do not all then that come, receive his body and blood?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This holy Sacrament is offered to all that judge themſelves worthy of it; but thoſe onely receive benefit from it, who are worthy in deed and in truth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>But ſuppoſe others do adventure to come who are unworthy, what do they receive?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> They receive their own deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, being guilty of the body and blood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Certainly then it is far better to abſtain from this ſacred banquet?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> There is a neceſſity lyes upon all Chriſtians to come, as alſo to come
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:97303:51"/>prepared, in regard this is the food of our ſoules, without which nouriſhment they will ſtarve and periſh; and alſo by neglecting this weighty concern, we ſhall diſobey the command of our dear Saviour, who hath ſolemnly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned us to keep this feaſt in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>What are the benefits whereof we partake by receiving the Lords Supper?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>The ſtrengthning and refreſhing of our ſouls by the body and blood of Chriſt, as our bodies are by the Bread and Wine.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How many are theſe benefits in number?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> They are two, firſt to ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and ſecondly, to refreſh our Soules.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In what meaſure are ſoules hereby ſtrengthned?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In the very ſame degree as out bodies are by bread, for as bread is the ſtaffe of life, without which the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is not able to ſubſiſt, but grows fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and weak, and at length drops
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:97303:52"/>into the grave, even ſo the body of Chriſt doth nouriſh and ſtrengthen our ſoules, enable them to the performance of good works, without which they have no power to decline the ways of ſin and death.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>In what meaſure are our ſoules refreſhed in this Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> In the ſame degree as our bodies are refreſhed by Wine; for as Wine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhes the body, not only when it is thirſtly, but alſo when it is faint and feeble, ſo doth the blood of Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh our Souls, waſh them from the guilt of Sin, which expoſed them to the wrath of God, which is the greateſt refreſhment, the moſt powerfull cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al that can be adminiſtred to them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>But how is it poſſible for ſo ſmall a piece of Bread, or one ſpoonful of Wine to produce ſuch rare effects?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Theſe proceed not from theſe outward elemens, but from the will and power of Chriſt, who was pleaſed to ordain theſe Elements as means and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:97303:52"/>inſtruments to conveigh theſe graces unto us.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>What is required of thoſe that come to the Lords Supper?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>To examine themſelves whether they repent them truly of their former fins, ſtedfaſtly purpoſing to lead a new life to have a lively faith in Gods mercy through Chriſt, with a thenkfull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his death; and to be in charity with all men.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is the general duty here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Examination; which is not only enjoyned by the Catechiſm, but the very ſame duty St. <hi>Paul</hi> requires of every one that come to this Table: <hi>let a man examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat of that bread, and drink of that Cup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What are thoſe matters about which every Chriſtian is not enquioe, or examine himſelf before this Feaſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> They are principally four; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:97303:53"/>Faith, Thankfulneſs, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is the firſt thing his exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation muſt ſpend it ſelf upon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The firſt matter muſt be Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What kind of repentance muſt a man find in himſelf, before he partakes of theſe Viands?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It muſt conſiſt of theſe two parts; Firſt, there muſt be an entire renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and forſaking of ſin, of every evil way; and Secondly, a ſtedfaſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and reſolution by Gods grace and aſſiſtance for the time to come to lead a new and innocent life.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is the ſecond matter he muſt bring under examination?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> His Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How muſt this Faith be quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It muſt be a lively Faith; which life it muſt ſhow forth by well doing; and it muſt alſo be a Faith in Gods mercy through Chriſt, that is, ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:97303:53"/>believing, that it is God alone, who, through the merits and ſufferings of his Son, hath given to mankind ſo great bleſſings as are beſtowed in this Sacrament?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is the third thing we muſt examine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> That is, our thankfulneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is it we muſt be thankful for?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> We muſt thankfully remember the death of Chriſt, what great things he hath done and ſuffered for us; and alſo with heart and voice we muſt make our returns of thanks unto this our compaſſionate Redeemer for this his infinite goodneſs and loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>What is the laſt duty we muſt exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our ſelves about?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It muſt be concerning our cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. As by repentance we muſt recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile our ſelves to God, ſo by charity we muſt reconcile our ſelves to our neighbours, before we dare come to this love-feaſt.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:97303:54"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>Wherein conſiſts this Chriſtian duty of Charity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It conſiſts of to parts; firſt, in giving to, and relieving the neceſſities of our poor diſtreſſed brethren; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly in forgiving and pardoning thoſe injuries and affronts which are offered to us by our neighbours.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> 
               <hi>How muſt this our Charity be qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It muſt be entire and univerſal, we muſt be in Charity with all men. And thoſe who come to this holy communion thus diſpoſed and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, their Souls ſhall be ſtrengthned and refreſhed by the body and blood of Chriſt, as their bodies are by the Bread and Wine.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:97303:54"/>
            <head>A Short TRACT of CONFIRMATION.</head>
            <p>THE Church of <hi>England</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns Godfathers and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothers, to take care that thoſe Children for whom they engage be brought to the Biſhop to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by him, ſo ſoon as they are well inſtructed in the Church Catechiſm; that is ſo ſoon as they can readily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe it, and give a reaſonable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the principles therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. But how remiſs and careleſs Sureties are in diſcharging this truſt which is repoſed upon them in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God and the Congregation, our own experience too badly enforms us; by which means this holy Rite of Confirmation is almoſt quite diſuſed: and it is to be feared, that it will in
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:97303:55"/>a ſhort ſpace of time be laid aſide, (notwithſtanding the pious care of our Reverend Father in God, not only by their Articles requiting all Miniſters in their ſeveral charges to prepare the younger ſort for the receiving of this divine Rite by Catechizing, and to bring them unto them, when by this means duly prepared, but alſo in their triennial viſitations confirming all ſuch as are brought unto them) if Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Sureties are not more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in inſtructing Children in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements of Religion; and, when by that means fitly quallified, in bringing them to receive this bleſſing from the hands of the Biſhop. And if we do but duly conſider the neceſſity of this Rite, and thoſe great bleſſings that do at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon it (as hereafter I ſhall manifeſt) it will then appear ſtrange, it ſhould be ſo generally ſlighted and omitted. The main cauſes of this neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence are either faction or ignorance. There are a generation of men in the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:97303:55"/>world, who being poſſeſſed with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of contradiction, diſuſe it, becauſe the higher Powers enjoyn it; they are heady, high-minded, deſpiſing domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and ſpeaking evil of dignities: and the great character of their Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip conſiſts in their oppoſition to the lawful Powers in thoſe matters which themſelves cannot prove to be illegal; and therefore becauſe confirmation is enjoyned by the Canon Law, becauſe it cannot be received but by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of the Biſhops (which they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominate as the members of Anti-Chriſt, and ſworn ſervants to the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi>) they reſolve to reject it (notwithſtanding the moſt evident reaſon that can be given to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) as a ſuperſtitious innovation, and a Popiſh Relique; and indeed ſo ſtrangely perverſe many of this rude hard are, that I am apt to perſwade my ſelf, ſhould the Supream Magiſtrate ſtrictly enjoyn thoſe fond opinions, which they do ſo zealouſly entertain,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:97303:56"/>they would forthwith Caſhiere them, to prevent the Powers from infring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Chriſtian Liberty; and this that Rebellious Principle which is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally entertained amongſt them, doth too evidently declare, <hi>viz.</hi> That thoſe things which in themſelves are lawful, become unlawful when en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by a lawful Authority: and as for theſe it will (I ſay) be a vain attempt to endeavour their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; indeed their own obſtinacy gives me reaſon to ſay, that it will prove almoſt as eaſie a task to waſh the Blackamore white, as to perſwade theſe zealous ſons of <hi>Korah,</hi> to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that againſt which they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed with too much prejudice and paſſion.</p>
            <p>But beſides theſe, there are another ſort of perſons who neglect this primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive inſtitution, out of pure ignorance; they underſtand little or nothing of the true meaning of it, and hence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds their omiſſion; neither can it at
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:97303:56"/>all ſeem ſtrange that ſo conſiderable a number of Chriſtians ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ignorant of the true notion of Confirmation, in regard it hath been generally diſuſed for ſo many years; ſo that they have ſcarce heard ſo much as the name of it until of late years, ſince the eſtabliſhment of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy; ſince which time they have poſsibly ſeen the name of it either in the Common Prayer Book, or in the Biſhop or Archdeacons Articles of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, and that is all the knowledge they have of it; and therefore to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move their Ignorance, I principally deſign this ſhort Treatiſe: neither am I altogether without hopes, but that it may have ſome good ſucceſs upon thoſe who propound to themſelves no other reaſon for their omiſſion, but their ignorance; for the removal wherefore, and the improving of their knowledge in a matter of ſo great weight (as hereafter I ſhall prove this to be,) I ſhall endeavour with as much
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:97303:57"/>clearneſs and plainneſs and brevity as may by, to ſhow, 1. What Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation is. 2ly. The lawfulneſs of it. 3ly. The neceſſity that all Chriſtians have to receive it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the true notion of Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, it is very well expreſſed in the word it ſelf, which is very full and ſignificant, for then we do confirm and are confirmed; from whence we may infer, that Confirmation conſiſts of two main Branches.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is an Act of Confirmation on our part, in regard we do hereby farther ratifie and eſtabliſh that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract or covenant which formerly, <hi>viz.</hi> at our baptiſm, was made betwixt <hi>God</hi> and us; and by confeſſing of it to be valid and Good, and by perſonally undertaking the ſtrict performance of it, we do profeſs our ſelves Gods faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſervants, and bind our ſelves faſter ſtill unto him, whoſe we were before; we do at the performance of this holy Rite, confirm what others, in our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:97303:57"/>acted on our behalf; we do then profeſs our ſelves bound both to believe and to do what our Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Godmothers promiſed for us; we do publickly own our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian profeſſion, profeſſing that we will be faithful in the diſcharge of our Baptiſmal vow.</p>
            <p>And it is very meet and convenient, that every Chriſtian ſhould perſonally reſume &amp; ratifie thoſe ſolemn engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that charitable perſons made for him in his infancy; neither can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man be reputed a true and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat member of the Church, until he do publickly own and profeſs, that he will faithfully ſtand to thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and terms that were made in his Name, when through the gate of Baptiſm he was graciouſly received into the number of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Holy <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church;</hi> that he will not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to confeſs the faith of <hi>Chriſt</hi> crucified, but couragiouſly continue &amp; perſevere in that high calling, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:97303:58"/>he is called, magure all oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the contrary, and manfully fight under <hi>Chriſts</hi> Banner againſt ſin, the world, and the Devil; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue <hi>Chriſts</hi> true and faithful Servant and Souldier to his lives end.</p>
            <p>And that this is the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> ſenſe of confirmation, is very plain from the office which is then to be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; which requires, that all perſons who are confirmed, ſhall audibly and publickly in the preſence of <hi>God</hi> and of the Congregation, renew that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn promiſe and vow that was made in their names at baptiſm, ratifying and confirming the ſame in their own perſons; and acknowledging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves bound to believe and do all thoſe things which their Godfathers and Godmothers then undertook for them; She only hereby intends that we ſhould be in reality and truth, what we out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly profeſs our ſelves; that as we at large bear the name of Chriſtians, Becauſe of the number, and living a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:97303:58"/>the Society of them, and in communion with them, ſo likewiſe we ſhould ſpecifie as much by our actions; having our <hi>Converſation ſuch as becometh the Goſpel of</hi> Chriſt <hi>denying all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and behaving our ſelves ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly, righteouſly, and godlily in this preſent evil world: which is no more than that duty which the Grace of God that hath appeared unto all men, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſalvation, hath taught us;</hi> It is no more than what we have ſtrictly obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged our ſelves to perform, when we took upon us the honourable name of Chriſtians; for then we faithfully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage to renounce the Devil and all his works, that is, <hi>to deny all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and to keep Gods holy will and Commandements, walking in the ſame all the dayes of our lives;</hi> whoſe ſacred Laws teach us to <hi>behave our ſelves ſoberly, righteouſly, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily in this preſent evil world.</hi> So that the Churches deſign is very good and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:97303:59"/>pious in continuing this wholſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; and as clearly oppoſite from either Superſtition or Will-worſhip, as light is from darkneſs; it is only the ſpiritual good of her ſons that ſhe would advance by the adminiſtration of this Rite; cauſe them openly to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg themſelves Gods faithful Servants; that they are reſolved by his aſſiſtance ſo to continue, chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and heartily performing his ſacred pleaſure; ſtopping up their cares, and barring up their hearts againſt all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and wicked inſinuations that may tempt them to the contrary.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. It is an Act of Confirmation on Gods part, who confers a new Grace to ſtrengthen in thoſe perſons that are confirmed, thoſe holy principles and that good reſolution, of which they have made a faithful profeſſion, and to enable them to continue and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in it; ſo that God doth confirm our confirmation, that is, he doth by the aſſiſtance of his good Spirit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:97303:59"/>and corroborate our reſolutions and purpoſes in performing our vow made at Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>The Reverent Biſhop of <hi>Down</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms us in his Epiſtle before his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe writ upon this very ſubject, that ſome wiſe and good men have piouſly believed (which is no ſmall addition to the honour of this Miniſtration) that when baptized perſons are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and bleſſed by the Biſhop, that then it is, that a ſpecial guardian Angel is appointed to keep their ſouls from the aſſaults of the Spirits of darkneſs: And all that he adds to it of his own ſentiments, is this, that the piety of this ſuppoſition is not at all diſagreeable to the intention of this Rite: for ſince by this, the holy ſpirit of God (the Father of all ſpirits) is given, it is not unreaſonably thought by them, that the other good Spirits of God, the Angels, who are miniſtring ſpirits, ſent forth to miniſter for their ſakes who are heirs of Salvation ſhould
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:97303:60"/>pay their kind offices in ſubordination to their Prince and Fountain. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can I diſcover any thing in this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion which is Heterodox, but that it may be very ſafely entertained; for if theſe glorious Angels (as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture enforms us) miniſter for the good of mankind, namely, that part of it as are obedient to the divine Laws of the great Soveraign of the Univerſe, then certainly there cannot be a more proper ſeaſon for them to enter upon this charitable employment, than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that age as it is requiſite for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation to be adminiſtred; and it is very agreeable both with the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs &amp; wiſdom of Almighty God, then to place the ſecureſt guard over his Servants, when they are the moſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſly aſſaulted by their ſpiritual e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, which is at the publick own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of themſelves to be <hi>Chriſts</hi> real members, and declare a profeſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt the Devil and all his works: when we openly profeſs Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:97303:60"/>and acknowledge out Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal vow, then it is that the rage of the Devil is moſt furious and violent, imagining if ever he can ſeduce us it will be at the firſt hand, before we are well ſettled and throughly groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in our holy reſolutions: But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, as the above mentioned Biſhop very well obſerves, there are greater and ſtranger things than this that God does for the ſoul of his Servants, and for the honour of the Miniſtries which himſelf hath appointed: and in this very Miniſtry will have the powerful aſſiſtance of the ſpirit of all ſpirits; the eternal ſpirit of God is our guide and our coadjutor to aſſiſt our own abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and undertakings, in abiding in that high calling whereunto we are called at our Baptiſm; he now by his gracious influence and bleſſed aid, helpeth our infirmities, and ſupplies our natural imperfections, making us able to do that which is good, and what the Lord requires of us. As in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:97303:61"/>the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> was conveyed as a ſanctifyer, ſo herein as a comforter and ſtrengthener, now that the perſon is entring upon a great conteſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict with himſelf, his own unruly luſts, the world, and principalities, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and ſpiritual wickedneſſes in high places. It is true, in Baptiſm we receive the Spirit of God, by it we are then regenerated, made members of <hi>Chriſt</hi> Children of God, and ſhall in the end be made inheritors of the Kingdom of <hi>Heaven,</hi> that is, if we continue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in the profeſſion of the Faith of <hi>Chriſt</hi> crucified, performing our part of the Covenant made in Baptiſm; to do which it requires a greater and more powerful aſſiſtance of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> which is given in confirmation.</p>
            <p>By Baptiſm we are Heirs, and are adopted to the inheritance of Sons, admitted to the Covenant of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and engaged to live a Godly life: yet, as the judicious Prelate learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly obſerves, this is but the Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:97303:61"/>of the Covenant, which muſt paſs into other Acts, by other influences of the ſame Divine Principle, untill we receive the Spirit of Obſignation and Confirmation; we are but Babes in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the meaneſt ſenſe, Infants that can do nothing, that cannot ſpeak, that cannot reſiſt any voilence, expoſed to every rudeneſs, and peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing by every temptation: But there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as God at the firſt appointed us a Miniſtry of a new birth in Baptiſm, ſo alſo hath he given to the Church the conſequent Miniſtery of a new ſtrength in Confirmation. The ſpirit moved a little upon the waters in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, by vertue of which motion it is made the Laver of Regeneration; ſo that by vertue of this Sacrament we receive the firſt Principles of life, are adopted into <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s family, made his living members, who before were dead in ſins and treſpaſſes. But in Confirmation he makes us able to move our ſelves; he ſo bountifully
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:97303:62"/>aſſiſts us, and ſo powerfully ſupplies our manifold infirmities, that we are able <hi>to work out our own Salvation with fear and trembling:</hi> In the firſt, he is the Spirit of life; but in this, he is the Spirit of ſtrength and motion: <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſma eſt nativitas, unguentum vero eſt actionis inſtra &amp; motus,</hi> as a learned Author obſerves; At the adminſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Baptiſm we are born again, we are received into the Congregation of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Flock, and are entitled to the glorious inheritance which he by his bloodſheding purchaſed for mankind; but in Confirmation we are enabled to move and act as becometh thoſe who are redeemed with ſo high a price. As in our natural birth we are firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants unable to help our ſelves, and are aſſiſted by Nurſes or others, who take the charge of us, to feed us and to lead us, and to aſſiſt us in every reſpect: but after ſome years our ſtrength encreaſes, and we are able to move and help our ſelves. Even ſo it
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:97303:62"/>is in our ſpiritual birth; firſt we are Babes in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> unable to move one ſtep in the paths of holineſs; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church in her wiſdom pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides Sureties, who receive the charge of us, to feed us with ſuch food as is convenient for us, to nouriſh us, to aſſiſt and adviſe us in the weighty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of our ſouls; but when we are at age to help our ſelves, then we take their care and truſt upon our own ſhoulders, ſtand upon our own legs, publickly promiſing to live the lives of Chriſtians, ſtrictly performing our ſolemn engagements which in time paſt was covenanted on our behalf: and to preſerve us from ſlipping and falling, the Spirit of God is given to aſſiſt our pious undertakings, and to ſtrengthen us in the encountring of thoſe raging enemies which we muſt expect to be aſſaulted with: and when good Chriſtian people had this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Confirmation, rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the true nature of it, they were
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:97303:63"/>then very zealous for it, and flocked in great multitudes to receive this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine miniſtry from the hands of the Biſhop. And time was in <hi>England</hi> (as Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi> relates) even ſince the firſt beginnings of Reformation, when Confirmation had been leſs carefully miniſtred for about ſix years, when the people had the firſt oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of it reſtored, they ran to it in ſo great numbers that Churches and Church-yards would not hold them, inſomuch that the Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi> was forced to impoſe hands on the people in the fields, and was ſo op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with the multitudes, that he had almoſt been trod to death by the people, and had died with the throng, if he had not been reſcued by the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Power: And it might have been hoped, that the diſuſe of it of late for ſo conſiderable a number of years, might have made it more highly pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed now that it is again reſtored; but alas our own experience finds it far
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:97303:63"/>otherwiſe, it continues ſtill too much neglected, not only for want of a right underſtanding of this holy Rite, but alſo by entertaining a belief that it is unlawful: many are deterred from deſiring this miniſtry, in regard that they are enformed that not one tittle of this is to be found in Gods word; and hereupon ſuppoſing it hath no Divine Warrant, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently condemn it as an Innovation, a piece of Will-worſhip, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently ſinful. VVherefore I ſhall in the next place prove the lawfulneſs of this Diſcipline; it is a plant of our Heavenly Fathers planting, and ſo no Innovation or VVill-worſhip; it is a Primitive and Apoſtolick Rite, and hath been continued in the Church in all Ages as a wholſom Diſcipline; and ſo no upſtart invention, or new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, to raiſe the Power, or advance the Grandeur of proud Prelates: and when I have cleared theſe two, then the lawfulneſs of this Rite will appear
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:97303:64"/>as clear as the Sun at the Noon day.</p>
            <p>This Divine Rite of Confirmation proceeds from above, it is warranted unto us by no meaner a perſon than the Eternal Son of God, who in his own perſon hath inſtituted and hallowed this Rite by ſubmiting unto it: no ſooner came he out of the waters, where he had been baptized by <hi>John,</hi> but immediately he is confirmed by the Spirit, which in the ſhape of a Dove deſcended upon him. He is now to enter upon the ſtage of the world, and to conflict with divers enemies; he is forthwith to be led into the VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs to be aſſaulted by the Prince of darkneſs, who now exerciſes all his cunning and malice to make a prey of this tender Lamb of God: But before he undertakes theſe hard tasks, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the living God reſts upon him; not that he had any need of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> or of his power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful aſſiſtance, in regard that infinite
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:97303:64"/>power that appertained to his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head was able to repel the greateſt rage of the Devil, and all his accurſed inſtruments; but all this was done for our ſakes, to inſtruct us in this ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of our Religion: he ſubmitted to this Rite, that we might follow his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and work out our Salvation by the ſame graces in the like ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities; which St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath very well expreſſed, affirming, <hi>Chriſti in Baptiſmo Columbam unctionem nostram preſiguraſſe,</hi> the Dove in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm did repreſent and prefigure out unction from above, that is, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> upon us in the Rite of Confirmation. And therefore to this and other external miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we muſt believe our ſelves obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to ſubmit, and make uſe of them in the working out our own Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being encouraged thereto by the preſident of this great Captain of our Salvation. <hi>Chriſt</hi> was Baptized and ſo muſt we; but after Baptiſm he had a
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:97303:65"/>new miniſtration for the reception of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> and becauſe this was done upon our account, therefore we muſt follow ſo good an example: And this being done immediately before his combate with that proud infernal Spirit, it plainly deſcribes unto us both the time when it ought to be received, as alſo that great advantage that attends the miniſtration of it.</p>
            <p>After we are baptized, when we are capable of underſtanding the ſolemn engagement of our Baptiſm, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon the perſonal performance of it, we have then great need to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in thoſe holy reſolutions and good purpoſes, and alſo ſtrengthened againſt thoſe fierce batteries and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate aſſaults that will be made upon us: We are now actually to renounce the Devil, the VVorld, and the Fleſh, to bid a bold and open defiance to all the works of Hell and Satan; and therefore we muſt receive the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the good Spirit of God, which
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:97303:65"/>is the deſign and proper work of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation. And this doth evidently manifeſt, not only the lawfulneſs but likewiſe the neceſſity of this Divine Rite; in imitation of the excellent pattern of our Saviour <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is the head of the Church, he entred this way upon his Duty and Work, not being thereto urg'd by neceſſity, but only to point out to us, which is the moſt proper and compendious way to gain a competency of ſtrength and power to enable us to perform our Chriſtian duty: him whom we are ſtrictly charged to follow as dear Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, was over ſhadowed with the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> juſt when he was entring upon the performance of that weighty work about which he came down from Heaven. Neither is this uſeful miniſtry only warranted unto us, by the preſident of the Holy <hi>Jeſus,</hi> the great exemplar to all ſucceeding ages, but alſo we find it diligently obſerved and duly practiſed in the firſt and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:97303:66"/>ages of Chriſtianity. The bleſſed Apoſtles in imitation of their great <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter,</hi> and by vertue of that Authority they received from him, confirm their converts, after that, by Baptiſm they are admited into the number of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Flock. After the Diſciples were endowed with power from on high, by being miraculouſly inſpired with the gifts of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> they communicate of the ſame Spirit to their Proſelytes to help their imperfections; and for this we have the plain expreſs words of Scripture, the relation whereof is recorded, Acts 8.14, 15, 16, 17. <hi>when the Diſciples that were at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>heard that</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria <hi>had received the word of</hi> God, <hi>they ſent unto them</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> John, <hi>who when they were come down, prayed for them that they might receive the</hi> Holy Ghoſt; <hi>for as yet he was fallen upon none of them, only they were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in the name of the Lord</hi> Jeſus; <hi>then laid they their hands on them, and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:97303:66"/>they received the</hi> Holy Ghoſt. Now if we do but duly obſerve theſe words, they give us a clear and full account of the whole order of this Divine Ritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here are the Perſons that are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of this miniſtry, thoſe that are baptized; and it is to ſuch only that the great bleſſing of the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> doth belong: it is only thoſe that through the Gate of Baptiſm are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the number of <hi>Chriſts</hi> flock, upon whom he will power down the gifts and graces of his holy Spirit by the miniſtration of his Embaſſadors.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Here is the time when this Apoſtolick Rite is adminiſtred, after Baptiſm. When by this holy Sacrament they had engaged themſelves in the practiſe of the true Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then was the ſeaſon that the holy Apoſtles by the laying on of hands, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated unto them a larger meaſure of the holy Spirit, to ſtrengthen them in the performance of thoſe Solemn
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:97303:67"/>engagements they then made.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Here was the manner how Confirmation was by theſe devout Perſons adminiſtred; it was by Prayer and laying on of hands.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Here are the only Miniſters of this Rite, two of the ſelect Apoſtles, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John: Philip</hi> the Evangeliſt who converted and baptized them, gave not the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> for he had not power ſo to do, for this gift was proper only to the Apoſtles, to none of the inferiour Paſtors or Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
            <p>And this very order doth the Church of <hi>England</hi> punctually obſerve in the adminiſtration of this Primitive Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline; ſhe confirms none but thoſe that are baptized; and the time when ſhe adminiſters it, is after baptiſme: and here indeed ſhe ſomething varies from the primitive practiſe, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed their converts preſently after Baptiſm, but ſhe not until a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable time afterwards, until the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:97303:67"/>are grown to years of diſcretion to underſtand their Baptiſmal vow; but there is very good reaſon for it, in regard thoſe <hi>Heathens</hi> which in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning were converted to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, were at age, when bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, to underſtand that promiſe they then made, and ſo were in a fit capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to be confirmed at that very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. She likewiſe adminiſters this Rite by prayer, and the laying on of hands; as alſo the Adminiſters here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are the Biſhops, who ſucceed in the place and ordinary office of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: So that the ſame thing that is now done in impoſition of hands, is no other than what was done by the firſt publiſhers of the Goſpel, ſuch as were inſpired and miraculouſly aſſiſted by an infallible Spirit; all deriving from the very ſame Authority. Our Church doth no more than what was practiſed in the firſt and pureſt ages of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, even by thoſe whoſe preſident is a very good Authority in this caſe.</p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:97303:68"/>
            <p>And now I am not able to conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture what can be ſaid againſt the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of confirmation, unleſs it ſhould be objected, that it was only ordained for a time, <hi>viz.</hi> for the Apoſtles time, and after it was to expire. But if I can prove that this miniſtry was not tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary and relative only to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time, but was to deſcend to the Church, and to continue with it for ever, and hereby to become a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual and never-ceaſing Miniſtry, I cannot then conceive what there is farther to be objected againſt the juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and lawfulneſs of this Rite. And firſt in order to this performance, let it be obſerved, that confirmation is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed and paſſed by St. <hi>Paul</hi> (if he may be ſuppoſed to be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor or the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi>) into a Chriſtian doctrine; in that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Epiſtle we ſhall find the Apoſtle to make impoſition of hands, namely, that which is the Ceremony in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, by which it was uſually
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:97303:68"/>known, a fundamental point, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. <hi>I ſhall ſet downe the very words, as tending very much to my preſent purpoſe. Therefore leaving the principles of the Doctrine of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>let us go on unto perfection, not laying again the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of repentance from dead works, and of Faith towards God, of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Baptiſm, and of laying on of hands, and of the Reſurrection of the dead, and of eternal judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here are ſix fundamental points of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Catechiſm, which he laid as the foundation or beginning of the inſtitution of Chriſtianity; and amongſt theſe, impoſition of hands is reckoned as a part of the foundation: and it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears very plaine to me, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle intends the very ſame impoſition of hands as was uſed in confirming the baptized, in regard it is placed imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after baptiſm, as being a diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline which was to follow upon it in order to the building up of a Chriſtian; now this being a ground work of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:97303:69"/>it muſt of neceſſity follow, that it muſt have the very ſame continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with it; the ſhalloweſt capacity eaſily apprehending, that when the foundation is rooted up, the whole Fabrick muſt be thrown down.</p>
            <p>But then again, this Miniſtry will appear to be of a larger continuance than the Apoſtles time, in regard that bleſſing which by this Miniſtry is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, is to abide with the Church for ever, <hi>viz.</hi> The benigne influence and aſſiſtance of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> When Our Saviour made this gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe at the firſt to his Diſciples, to give them the comforter, he was to abide with them to the end of the world, <hi>John</hi> 14.16. <hi>And I will pray the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and he ſhall ſend you another Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, that he may abide with you for ever, even the Spirit of Truth.</hi> And we ſhall find, that when this gift was ſo miraculouſly beſtowed upon the holy Apoſtles at the day of <hi>Penticoſt,</hi> inſomuch that thoſe who were Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſes
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:97303:69"/>were ſtrangly amazed, and marvelled to hear them ſpeaking in divers languages, at that very ſame time St. <hi>Peter,</hi> to take off the ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the wonder, and the envy of the power, tels them in plain terms, that upon condition they would <hi>Repent and be baptized, they ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of them receive the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> not the meaneſt, the moſt inconſiderable amongſt them but ſhould receive that great thing which they obſerved in them; and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly themſelves, but their Children alſo: <hi>For the promiſe is to you and to your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and to all that are afar off, even to as many as the Lord our God ſhall call, Acts</hi> 2.38, 39. Now it is very unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to ſuppoſe, that the Rite (which is partly moral and partly cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial, the firſt is prayer, the other is laying on of hands) that this ſhould be tranſient only for a ſhort time, when as the promiſe it ſelfe is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue for ever. It cannot but ſeem
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:97303:70"/>very ſtrange, that a ſolemn Rite an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to a perpetual promiſe ſhould be tranſient and temporary. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is of a bleſſing to endure for ever, the Ceremony or Rite was annexed to the promiſe, and therefore this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo muſt be for ever. And as this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry was to continue for ever, ſo was it duly obſerved and actually practiſed by the ſucceeding Ages of the Church, as the Reverent Biſhop of <hi>Down</hi> in his Treatiſe upon this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject hath very learnedly proved: And certainly, next after the plain words of Scripture, the univerſal tradition of the Church is the beſt argument for the probation of Rituals; And what I have hitherto diſcourſed of, the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of this Rite, is certainly ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſatisfie every reaſonable perſon of the neceſſity of it: for that which is Authorized by no meaner a Perſon than the Eternal Son of God, which was practiſed by the Holy Apoſtles, was obſerved in the pureſt ages of
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:97303:70"/>Chriſtianity, and is a never-ceaſing Miniſtry, muſt of neceſſity both be lawful to be done, and very meet and convenient to be retained in practiſe.</p>
            <p>But in regard there is nothing more powerfully prevailes with mankind than their intereſts, I ſhall in the laſt place (in order to the proving the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of this wholſom Diſcipline, and to encourage all to the due obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it,) endeavour to manifeſt thoſe great graces and excellent privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges which are conſequent to the worthy reception and due Miniſtry of it. When Confirmation is rightly performed and worthily received, it will be highly advantagious to us, and will greatly promote the Spiritual good and intereſt of every Chriſtian, and therefore ought not by any means to be neglected: And in this reſpect the Scripture hath ſpoken ſo fully &amp; plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as is abundantly ſufficient to prove that great bleſſing that waits upon us.</p>
            <p>It is recorded by St. <hi>Luke</hi> in the <hi>Acts</hi>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:97303:71"/>of the <hi>Holy Apoſtles,</hi> that at the firſt miniſtration of this Rite they received the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> that is, according to the expreſſion of the <hi>Holy Jeſus</hi> to his Diſciples, when he commanded them to tarry at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in expectation of the accompliſhment of his glorious promiſe; they are endowed with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue from on high, that is, with ſtrength to perform their duty, to perſevere in their Chriſtian profeſſion, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the oppoſition of Satan and his accurſed inſtruments. So that this power from on high, which is the proper bleſſing of Confirmation, was expreſſed, not only with ſpeaking of Tongues and doing Miracles, but it was effected in ſpiritual and inward ſtrengths; They were not only ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for the ſervice of the Church, to ſpeak in a languages for the benefit of all nations, and to do mighty works to convince <hi>Gain-ſayers,</hi> but alſo they were endowed with courage and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Chriſtian fortitude, and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:97303:71"/>openly to <hi>confeſs the faith of Chriſt crucified, and manfully to fight under his Banner, againſt Sin, the World, and the Devil, and to continue Chriſts faithful Servants and Souldiers to their lives end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if we do but duly conſider how apt we are to erre out of the way of Gods Commandments, to ſtart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide like a broken Bow, and what great oppoſition we meet with in run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Race that is ſet before us, we ſhall find abundance of reaſon to make uſe of all lawful means to gain a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er meaſure and aſſiſtance of Gods good Spirit, That Body of death which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſo earneſtly deſired to be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from, that old man of Sin, our Rebellious Wills and Affections, do fatally reſiſt all good motions and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations within us.</p>
            <p>This Law in our members is conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually warring againſt the Law in our minds, and bringing us into cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity to the law of ſin, that is in our
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:97303:72"/>members; but when this Allmighty Spirit deſcends upon us, he ſupplies us with ſuch a meaſure of ſtrength as enables us to mortifie all our earthly Members, to keep them under ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to vanquiſh all thoſe proud luſts of the fleſh which lead us Captive to the committance of evil.</p>
            <p>But beſides theſe inward, we have alſo outward enemies, the Devil and his accurſed Retinue, which bandy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether their Forces to overcome us, and draw us into their ſnares and Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalage; theſe exerciſe all their malice and cunning to provoke us to renounce our ſolemn Baptiſmal engagements, and to walk in a down-right oppoſition to that duty our Maker expects from us. When we are once engaged in a holy profeſſion, and have faithfully covenanted to forſake every evil pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe that is unworthy this our high cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, then is the time that our grand adverſary, fearing that he ſhall loſe a proſellyte, will violently oppoſe us,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:97303:72"/>he will make us promiſes as large as heart can either wiſh or deſire; nay he will not ſtand out for any thing, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than loſe a Diſciple; he will out of deſign court us at an exceeding high rate, telling us, as he did our Saviour, that all the kingdoms of the world, with their glory, are at his diſpoſal; ſo that nothing ſhall be wanting to compleat our deſires, that this world can afford, will we but throw off the yoak of our dear Saviour, and liſt our ſelves under his accurſed banner: And we ſhall find theſe ſuch prevailing temptations as fleſh and blood cannot eaſily reſiſt. But when we are endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with vertue from on high, it will enable us both to diſcover his deluſions and to reſiſt his greateſt force and fury. That infinite power which at the firſt threw the Prince of darkneſs from his primitive eſtate of happineſs and perfection, is able to guard us from all his aſſaults, that we may paſs on cheerfully in the performance of what
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:97303:73"/>the Lord requires of us. And indeed this is the principal bleſſing of Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; our ſpiritual ſtrength here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is augmented; that new life which we receive at Baptiſm, is now ſo heightned and improved, that we are able to live the lives of good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and in a very good meaſure to perform what our Sureties promiſed for us. So that Confirmation is the conſummation and perfection, the corroboration and ſtrength of Baptiſm and baptiſmal grace; for in baptiſm we undertake to do our duty, but in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation we receive a new ſupply of ſtrength for the doing of it; in baptiſm others promiſe for us, in confirmation we undertake for our ſelves; we eaſe our Godfathers and Godmothers of their burden, and taken it upon our own ſhoulders: In Babtiſme we give up our names to Chriſt, but in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation we put our ſeal to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and God puts his Seal to the promiſe; we enter then upon the actual
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97303:73"/>performance of our Baptiſmal vow, which includes the whole of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian duty; and then it is that God poures down his holy Spirit upon us, to direct and guide us in thoſe weighty things that relate to our eternal peace, ſo that in confirmation we receive an encreaſe of the Spirit of grace where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are ſtrengthned unto battel, prepared to recieve the deſperate aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults and fierce encounters of our mercyleſs adverſaries: to which I ſhall only add what St. <hi>Cyrill</hi> argues from the deſcenſion of the holy Ghoſt upon Chriſt after his baptiſm, whoſe words I ſhall ſet down as I find them quoted by the Biſhop of <hi>Down:</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">When he was baptized in the River <hi>Jordan,</hi> he aſcended out of the Waters, and the holy Ghoſt ſubſtantially deſcended upon him, like reſting upon like: And ſo you alſo, in like manner, after ye have aſcended from the waters of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, the unction is given which bears the image or ſimilitude of him by
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:97303:74"/>whom Chriſt was anointed; that as Chriſt after Baptiſm and the coming of the holy Spirit upon him, went forth to battel in the wilderneſs, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the adverſary; ſo ye alſo after holy Baptiſm and the myſtical unction (or confirmation) being veſted with the armour of the holy Spirit, are ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to ſtand againſt the oppoſite powers</q> ſo that certainly were this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent favour duely conſidered that attends confirmation, it would be ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved by all thoſe who in any competent meaſure intend their own eternal good and happineſs.</p>
            <p>But beſides all this, many benefits will accrue to us by performing our parts in confirmation, that is, by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly in our own perſons under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking thoſe ſolemn engagements that was by others made on our behalf at Baptiſm: It is the opinion of a very learned perſon, <q rend="margQuotes">That there could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be a well conſtituted Church without this practiſe; nor can we tell
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97303:74"/>that men are not Heathens and Pagans, and have not revoked their word, unleſs they will openly acknowledge that they underſtand what they then did, and will not ſtir from it. VVill any man be aſhamed (ſaith the ſame Author) to make ſuch a profeſſion, and to tread in the way of Chriſts Church, becauſe it hath been of late diſuſed or turned into another thing? VVhy ſhouldeſt thou bluſh to own holineſs, to ſay before Chriſt's Church, thou art reſolved to lead a Chriſtian life, and renounce the Devil and all the ways of wickedneſs? why ſhouldeſt thou be aſhamed of thy Religion, as if it were fit to be profeſſed only in a private corner, where none ſhould hear thee? VVhy ſhould it be accounted a ſtrange thing to proteſt love to God?</q> it is an honour and glory unto us that we may be Chriſtians, and ſo ſhould we eſteem it: we ſhould be right glad of an opportunity, wherein we may do our ſelves ſo much honour, as to tell the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97303:75"/>world that we are and reſolve to be the real diſciples and faithful fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of the eternal King of Glory. We ſhall alſo find divers great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits to enſue upon the renewing of our vow in the preſence of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This will be a means to make us more ſtrictly and conſcientiouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the rules and duties of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: when we conſider, that we have acquainted the world with our good reſolutions, that they know what a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn profeſſion we have made to lead a virtuous and a Chriſtian life in all godlineſs and honeſty, then we cannot for ſhame but practice what we have ſo openly profeſſed, our own credit will make us afraid to commit a ſin againſt which we have ſo ſolemnly and publickly profeſſed; and we ſhall eaſily believe that every one will up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid us with the breach of promiſe, when they ſee us to act contrary to what we once told the congregation;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:97303:75"/>we ſhall hereby force the world to believe us falſe and perfidious, not our words Maſter; neither can we imagine that any perſon that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands his own intereſt will take our word, or truſt to our promiſe in any matter that relates to theſe temporal affairs, when as we dare break thoſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn promiſes, upon every ſlight occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, every inconſiderable temptation that is offered, that we make in the preſence of God and a whole congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation: ſo that our credit will ingage us, when we have once made a publick engagement, to ſtand by it, not to ſhrink from it, but to be diligent in the obſervation of every part of it. Secondly, This renewing our Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal vow in the preſence of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, will be a ſoveraign antidote againſt the allurements of Satan; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can we have a better preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive againſt his force and fury, than to tell him what we told the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that now we are reſolved (having
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:97303:76"/>paſſed our word for it) that we will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce him, and all that appertains unto him, and be Gods faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to our lives end. When we are able confidently to tell this bold temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that we have no room to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him, having engaged our ſelves in the face of the world to wage a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual war againſt him, and alſo vowed Loyalty &amp; Fidelity to our eternal Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, we need not doubt but that this will drive him away from us, and alſo for the time to come diſcourage him from making ſuch frequent attempts upon us. Neither will this only be a means to preſerve us from the daring onſets of the Prince of Darkneſs, but alſo it will very much ſecure us from the inſinuation of his agents, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſons of <hi>Belial.</hi> Wicked men certainly cannot have the con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ence to ask us to ſin, when we have ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely profeſſed againſt it; evill company will ſhun and avoid us, when they know that we are not of their
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:97303:76"/>foot-marks, but have publickly diſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their ungodly practiſes, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. You complain of lewd ſociety, of friends and acquaintance that draw you into many inconveniences; do but let them know that you intend to be religious, and they will let you alone. The Philoſophers openly profeſſed a ſevere and unuſual life, that all men might let them live Philoſophically, and not be a diſturbance unto them. Let but us do ſo, and be profeſſedly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and they will have the leſs boldneſs for to trouble us. Our work is half done when we are heartily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved; and more than half done, when we publickly profeſs theſe our good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This open renewing of our Baptiſmal engagements wil very much lead to the bringing of Religion into faſhion, and to make it a thing very creditable and honorable: When men openly appear for it, and are not aſhamed publiquely to confeſs and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97303:77"/>acknowledge it, then the perverſe ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> will be diſcouraged from ſcoffing and reproaching of it; it will ſtop the mouths of all gainſayers, when they behold the greateſt and ſobereſt part of mankind to countenance it, by profeſſing ſeriouſly to practiſe it. And this certainly will mightily prevail with all thoſe as have any kindneſs or honour for Religion, openly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new their vows, eſpecially in this care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs age, wherein Atheiſm and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs have joyned forces to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance, yea, utterly to baniſh all Religion from amongſt us.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The open owning of our Baptiſmal vow, wil be a great prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, in order to the receiving the holy Sacrament of Chriſts moſt precious body and blood; neither is it meet that any ſhould be admitted to ſo neer a communion with Chriſt, who will not openly acknowledge and promiſe fealty and obedience to his Sacred commands And therefore what our
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:97303:77"/>Church enjoyns in this caſe, is very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, <hi>viz.</hi> that none ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the holy Communion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſuch time as he be confirmed, or be ready and deſirous to be confirmed: and therefore if we intend to receive Chriſt in the Sacrament, to feed upon his body and blood, which is ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent food, as moſt certainly will nouriſh our ſouls to life eternal, it is but very meet and convenient that we ſhould firſt openly profeſs our ſelves his members and ſervants, and that we reſolve ſo to continue; this will reduce us into a fit capacity to feed at the Lords Table, whereby we may encreaſe in ſtrength, &amp; enjoy a more intimate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt. And indeed, until this is done, I may juſtly ſay, men are but imperfect members, babes and infants in Chriſt, and not to be admitted (in the judgment of all ages) to taſt of the meat of men, until they ſhew themſelves to be men by ſpeaking for themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:97303:78"/>
            <p>And to all this I ſhall only add the miſery that in the end ſhall attend thoſe that will not make an open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſt; as alſo the priviledge that they ſhall enjoy who are free to perform this ſo reaſonable a duty; and this I ſhall give you in our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours own words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.72. <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall confeſs me before men, him will I confeſs before my Father which is in Heaven;</hi> That is, will confeſs him to be one of my flock, my true diſciple and member, and accordingly will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him; <hi>but whoſoever ſhall deny</hi> me before men (and certainly he that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed openly to profeſs Chriſt, will not be afraid to deny him, if moved thereto either by fear or advantage) <hi>him will I alſo deny before my Father which is in Heaven.</hi> And it is not within the power of any man to imagine how dreadful and inſupportable their doom will be, who are denyed and diſowned by the great Judg of Heaven and Earth. So that now I cannot ſee what there is
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:97303:78"/>to deter men from ſubmitting to this wholſome diſcipline, it being not only neceſſary, but alſo highly reaſonable, that we ſhould openly promiſe to be his faithful ſervants, who both created us, and redeemed us. Why ſhould we not as freely and readily promiſe in the face of the congregation, obedience to Gods ſacred pleaſure and commands, as we do allegiance and loyalty to our Prince before a Court of Juſtice? If it is reaſonable that we ſhould be obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the laws of our Maker, which no Chriſtian will deny; what harm is their in making an open profeſſion that we will be ſo? and therefore it would be very happy, and cannot but be earneſtly deſired by all good Chriſtians, that all animoſities and vain janglings might be quite layed aſide, and that we may all joyn together in practiſing whatſoever may advance us forward towards the end of our hopes, the Salvation of our Souls.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
